<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The accompt rekenynge and confession of the faith of Huldrik Zwinglius byshop of Zuryk the chief towne of Heluetia sent vnto Charles the fyfte nowe Emperoure of Rome, holdynge a counsel wyth the moost noble princes, estates and learned men of Germany assembled together at Ausburgh. 1530. in the moneth of Iuly. Translated out of latyn by Thomas Cotsforde. And imprinted at Geneua. In April. 1555.</title>
            <title>Ad Carolum Romanorum imperatorem Germaniae comitia Augustae celebrantem, fidei Huldrychi Zuinglij ratio. English</title>
            <author>Zwingli, Ulrich, 1484-1531.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1555</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 184 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15880</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26140</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120361</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855560</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855560</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21056</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15880)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21056)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 603:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The accompt rekenynge and confession of the faith of Huldrik Zwinglius byshop of Zuryk the chief towne of Heluetia sent vnto Charles the fyfte nowe Emperoure of Rome, holdynge a counsel wyth the moost noble princes, estates and learned men of Germany assembled together at Ausburgh. 1530. in the moneth of Iuly. Translated out of latyn by Thomas Cotsforde. And imprinted at Geneua. In April. 1555.</title>
                  <title>Ad Carolum Romanorum imperatorem Germaniae comitia Augustae celebrantem, fidei Huldrychi Zuinglij ratio. English</title>
                  <author>Zwingli, Ulrich, 1484-1531.</author>
                  <author>Cottesford, Thomas.</author>
                  <author>Holy Roman Empire. Reichstag (1530 : Augsburg, Germany)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 92, 83-109, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Egidius Van der Erve,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Geneva, i.e. Emden :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1555]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Ad Carolum Romanorum imperatorem fidei ratio.</note>
                  <note>The imprint is false; printed in Emden by Egidius Van der Erve (STC).</note>
                  <note>Includes two epistles by Thomas Cottesford.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 26140a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21056:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21056:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The accompt <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenynge and confeſſion of the faith of Huldrif Zwinglius byſhop of</hi>
               </hi> Zuryk the chief towne of Heluetia, ſent vnto Charles the fyfte nowe Emperoure of Rome, holdynge a counſel wyth the mooſt noble Prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, Eſtates and learned men of Germany aſſembled together at Auſburgh. <hi>1530.</hi> in the moneth of Iuly.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Math. 11.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <hi>Come vnto me all ye that labour and are laden, and I wyll refreſh you.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>3. <hi>Eſdr.</hi> 3.</bibl> 
               <hi>Aboue all thynges truth hath the victorye.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Auguſtyne.</bibl> Truthe maye be oppreſt for a tyme but it can not be ouercome.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of latyn by Thomas Cotſforde. And imprinted at Geneua. In April. 1555.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:21056:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21056:2"/>
            <head>The contentes of thys hole boke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>¶Of the vnitie &amp; Trinitie of God, and of Chriſte the ſonne of God, and the ſonne of man. pag. 3.</item>
               <item>¶Of two Natures in one perſone, and that the diſtincte properties and operations of the two natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res in Chriſte diuide not the per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſone. 4.</item>
               <item>¶The weaknes of mans Frewyl, and of Goddes gracious proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. pag. 8.</item>
               <item>¶Of mans creacion and of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des goodneſſe, mercy and rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes. pag. 9</item>
               <item>¶Of Chriſtes incarnacion pag. 10</item>
               <item>¶The only medicin of the ſicke ſoule pag. 11</item>
               <item>¶Chriſt is the only waye to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliacion and true felicitie, &amp; that iuſtificacion of workes, merites prayers and interceſſion of ſain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes are confuted, and of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicion of Goddes eleccion pag. 12</item>
               <item>¶Of original ſynn. pag. 13. 14</item>
               <item>¶Synne is the cauſe of mans my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerye. pag. 15</item>
               <item>¶The ſtate of bondage ſpryngethth of the faulte. pag. 17</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:21056:3"/>
               <item>¶It is raſſhnes to condempne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantes dyeng wythout baptyme of water. pag. 18</item>
               <item>¶Infantes of Chriſtianes by the promyſe made vnto theyr paren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes are membres of the churche pag. 19. 20.</item>
               <item>¶Of the churche of the Electe. pag. 21</item>
               <item>¶The felicitie of fayth is to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded that he is the inheritoure of eternall lyfe pag. 22</item>
               <item>¶Of the vniuerſal and ſenſible Churche pag. 23</item>
               <item>¶Euel as wel as good are contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in it pag. 24</item>
               <item>¶The Chriſten fathers, mothers, Godfathers and godmothers &amp; the Churche it ſelfe acknowlege theyr infantes to be membres of it pag. 26</item>
               <item>¶Sacramentes gyue not grace pag. 28</item>
               <item>¶By Sacramentes we witneſſe to the churche, that we haue recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the grace of God. pag. 31</item>
               <item>¶What a Sacrament is, and that Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes repreſent the agre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment done by the ſpirite. pag. 33</item>
               <item>¶Of the holy Supper of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde pag. 35</item>
               <item>¶Chriſtes body occupieth place pag. 41</item>
               <item>¶The only ſpirite gyueth ſpiritual
<pb facs="tcp:21056:3"/> thynges pag. 43</item>
               <item>¶Thre argumentes againſt the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dely preſence of Chriſtes natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral bodye in the Supper pag. 45. 46.</item>
               <item>¶The olde wryters ſpake ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally when they reaſoned of the frute of eatynge Chriſtes bodye in the Supper. pag. 49.</item>
               <item>¶Of Ceremonies, and that yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ought to be taken awaye yf there be any peryl of worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge them. pag. 51.</item>
               <item>¶Of Monſtrouſe mytred byſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes. pag. 53</item>
               <item>¶Of the office of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Magiſtrate pag. 54</item>
               <item>¶Of the Popes Purgatory pag. 55</item>
               <item>¶Of Hell. pag. 56</item>
               <item>¶The frutes of true doctrine. pag. 61</item>
               <item>¶The frutes of mennes tradicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. pag. 62.</item>
               <item>¶An Epiſtle declaryng the confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſynnes pag. 65</item>
               <item>¶Of a general confeſſion of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. pag. 67</item>
               <item>¶Confeſſion of ſynnes vnto God only pag. 69</item>
               <item>¶Confeſſion of ſynnes before men pag. 72</item>
               <item>¶Priuate confeſſion of ſynnes is nedeful to many for knowlege,
<pb facs="tcp:21056:4"/> counſel and comforte pag. 74</item>
               <item>¶Howe it is nedeful for knowlege pag. 74. 75.</item>
               <item>¶Howe it is nedeful for cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel pag. 76</item>
               <item>¶Howe a ſynner ſhal recouer god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des fauour. pag. 80</item>
               <item>¶Nyne preſeruatiues from whor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom pag. 81. 82.</item>
               <item>¶Priuate confeſſion is nedeful for comforte pag. 82</item>
               <item>¶To whome chefly one ought to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe hys ſynnes pag. 86</item>
               <item>¶What is true abſolucion of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes pag. 86</item>
               <item>¶Of confeſſion of reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciliacion pag. 87.</item>
               <item>¶An open confeſſion to the churche pag. 89</item>
               <item>¶Abuſes of eare confeſſion. pag. 90 91. 62. 93</item>
               <item>¶The erroure of the Nouacions &amp; Anabaptiſtes pag. 96</item>
               <item>¶Thre ſortes of ſynnes, one is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſynne, an other blaſphemye, the thyrd, blaſphemye agaynſte the ſpirite or ſynne agaynſt the holy ghoſt. pag. 110</item>
               <item>¶What is Synne. pag. 111</item>
               <item>¶What is blaſphemye pag. 111. 112. 113</item>
               <item>¶What is the ſynne agaynſt the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye
<pb facs="tcp:21056:4"/> ghoſt. pag. 114.</item>
               <item>¶Daniels prayer in Metre. pag. 116</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Fautes eſcaped.</head>
            <p>¶Gentle reader before thou reade it ouer wyth thy penne mende the fautes eſcaped, begynnynge with the cyphers on the toppe of the pages. thus:</p>
            <p>¶Next after the page. 91. me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the cyphers of thre pages immediat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly folowyng thus: 92. 93. 94. and ſo folowyng from 95. vnto the ende of the boke.</p>
            <p>Page. 29. lyne. 13. reade brought</p>
            <p>Page. 39. lyne. 5. reade after</p>
            <p>Page. 51. in the margin, read it thus Images oughte to be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye yf ther. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Page. 57. the fyrſt worde of the firſt lyne reade: beleue.</p>
            <p>Page. 77. lyne. 26, read publicanes</p>
            <p>Page. 80. laſt lyne ſcrape out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt worde (he)</p>
            <p>Page. 81. lyne. 14. read: auoyde.</p>
            <p>Page. 91. lyne. 13. reade: for they thynke</p>
            <p>Page. 97. lyne. 22. read: of the wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21056:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To all hys faythfull brethren and ſyſters other willyngly fled or</hi> ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannouſly exyled out of Englande for Chriſtes Goſpel ſake, Thomas Cotſforde wyſſheth from God the father thorow our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt much incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſe of fayth, godly kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wlege and conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in Chriſtes holy reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>DEarly beloued, whan I</hi> wyth a lamentable hert conſyder wyth my ſelfe the myſerable ſtare of Englande my natiue cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treye, and the great ouerthrowe of Chriſtes pure religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there, ſythe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſte dolorouſe death of our moſte godly and vertuouſe prince, Kynge <hi>Edwarde</hi> the ſyxt: and agayne remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brynge howe Idolatrie, ſuperſtici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Papiſtrie, and al kyndes of falſe worſhippinge of God hathe in ſo ſhorte tyme ouerflowed ſo noble a realme: and what an infinite nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre (which wythin theſe two yeares
<pb facs="tcp:21056:5"/> paſt bare a fayre face towards true religion) are now ſuddenly turned backe to worſhip the beaſt, that is, to enbrace the Babilonicall ſtrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and to taſte agayne of the cuppe of her abhominacions, I can ſcant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye refrayne myne herte from ſob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bynge, and myne eyes from diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge of teares. Alaſſe for pytie, what a great no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of Goddes peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is thys day within Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that in theyr hertes do deteſte &amp; abhorre that falſe worſhippinge and great diſhonourynge of God nowe vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently (I wyl not ſaye tyrannouſly) thruſt into euery churche and chap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pel, and wolde wyth all theyr her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes (yf they knew whyche waye to bringe it to paſſe) flye out of that Ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bylon nowe the great cytie of ſynne and confuſion? And contrary wyſe it wolde pytie any true chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes herte to remembre how many ther are wythin that realme (which are fully perſuaded in theyr conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences concerninge true religion) that myght wel enough eſcape and come away, &amp; yet wyl not: but ſome of them had rather wyth moſte ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfeſt and ſhamefull ydolatrie pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
<pb facs="tcp:21056:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> both theyr ſoules and theyr bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, than they wolde forſake the pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parynge of theyr paunches, &amp; theyr beſt beloued God the wycked Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. Other ther be that ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence that they maye tary wel enou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghe and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nicate wyth the ydo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrers: but I maruell wyth what conſciences they can other reade or heare theſe and ſuche lyke places of ſcripture here followynge:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</note>Beare not a ſtraunge yoke (ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſaynt Paule) wyth the vnbele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers: for What felowſhip hath righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſnes wyth vnryghteouſnes? What co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany hath lyght wyth dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneſſe? What co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>corde hath Chriſte wyth Belial? &amp;c. Howe agreeth the temple of God wyth ymages? And it foloweth: Come awaye out from amonge them, and ſeparate youre ſelues (ſayeth the Lorde) and touche none vncleane thynge, ſo wyl I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue you. &amp;c. Doutleſſe me thynke that thys texte reherſed ſhulde ſore nyppe theyr conſciences co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydering that the Lorde hymſelfe ſpeaketh it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 18.</note>Let them weye alſo thys ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: Come awaye my people from Babilon (that is, from that cytie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme,
<pb facs="tcp:21056:6"/> towne, village, houſe, familie and company, whiche openly diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth God by ydolatrie, ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion and falſe worſhippyng) that ye be not partakers of her ſinnes, that ye receaue not of ther plages.</p>
            <p>Againe, let them remembre this ſayeng of the prophete Elias:<note place="margin">3. Reg. 18.</note> Why halt ye betwene two opinions? Yf the Lorde be the true God folowe hym? But yf Baal be he, than folow hym.<note place="margin">An excuſe</note> But many excuſe them ſelues by a boke made and compiled by a great clerke that dyed wyth in theſe fyue yeres paſt: whych boke (as they ſaye) maketh muche for theyr pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that is, for goynge to the wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Maſſe. &amp;c. But ſurely, yf they weye that boke wel, it maketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge for them at al: for he wrote that parte of hys boke for them that were but yonglynges in the true knowlege and vnderſtandynge of the myſteries of Chriſtes religion, and dwelt in ſuche a realme or cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treye that were cleane ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med wyth Papiſtrie, and not well reformed as was Englande. He wrote not that for them that hadde ben already wel nuſeled and exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:21056:7"/> in true religion many yeares (as ſome of theſe excuſers haue) and are fullye perſuaded already in the greateſt miſteries of pure religion. I dare ſaye, yf he were alyue he wolde not iuſtifye, neither beare wyth theſe men, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e God hath geuen ſo plentie of true knowlege, and that ſo many yeares ago, but wolde mooſte ſharply rebuke them and tel them playnly, that theyr ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companiyng and fellouſhip in falſe worſhipping with ydolatrers ſhuld <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> moſte manifeſtly extende: Fyrſt to the great diſhonour of the omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Lorde their God. Secondarely to the accuſacion and condempna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of theyr owne conſciences, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge ſo manyfeſt places of holye <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ſcripture agaynſt them: Thyrdly, to the great offence of their yonge and weake chriſten brethren, whych ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue many yeares knowen theyr opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> touchyng religion. And final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to the confirmacion of the olde ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cred and ruſtie Papiſtes in theyr groſſe erroures and blyndneſſe.</p>
            <p>But the ſoreſt grefe of al vnto myn herte (were it not that theyr bolde confeſſion of theyr fayth and ſtoute
<pb facs="tcp:21056:7"/> ſtanding and conſtant perſeuering in the ſame vnto the death comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth me agayne) is the tyrannicall ſlaughter and butcherlike murther of the ſaintes, whych were the true ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of God, the ſyncere prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the waye of ſaluacion, the veray martyrs, true wytneſſes and conſtant confeſſoures of the true fayth of Ieſus Chriſt, whych of late in Englande haue beſtowed theyr veray lyues for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teſtimony of that truth, whyche they haue in tymes paſt ſo faythfully preached to many thouſandes of Chriſten ſoules with in that realme.</p>
            <p>O Englande, Englande, what a ſore buffet hath God now gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee: Partlye, by reſtorynge that bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuckyng byſhop the Romyſhe Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt to hys former vſurped autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in that goodly realme, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye to Goddes worde, contrarye to thyne owne lawes, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to al your othes, faith and fydelitie, to thy perpetual ſhame ſo longe as the worlde ſhal endure: And partly, by takynge awaye from thee ſuche notable Inſtrumentes, by whoſe mouthes thou haſt abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dantly herd
<pb facs="tcp:21056:8"/> God ſpeake vnto thee, and moſte lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyngly ſhewed thee how thou migh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſt be ſaued, and in ſteade of them in hys heauy diſpleaſure nowe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freth thy ſhameleſſe ſhepherdes out of al pulpettes to fede the wyth too ſhameful lyes? And why? Doutleſſe moſte worthely. Becauſe, (as S. Paule ſayeth) thou receauedſt not the loue of the truthe (when thou myghteſt haue hadde it) that thou myghteſt haue ben ſaued:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Teſſ.</hi> 2.</note> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God ſhal ſende thee ſtronge de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>luſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that thou ſhuldeſt beleue lyes. But take hede. For prate they neuer ſo monſtrouſe lyes, glorious Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dener and butcherlyke Boner with other of that ruflynge route of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſhe rutters, ſhall ſet ſuche a gly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterynge gloſe vpon them, and with ſuche counterfeted coloures ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forth &amp; paynt them, that thou ſhalte thynke them to be moſte certaine &amp; Euangelicall truthes, and ſhalte be brought into ſuche dotage and ſo be bewitched, that thou ſhalt thynke, that cheſe is chalke, and chalk cheſe. Swete is ſowre, and ſowre ſwete, good is euel,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 5.</note> and euel good, and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſequently, that truth is lyes, &amp; lyes
<pb facs="tcp:21056:8"/> are truthes. And yet to ſay the truth it is maruel, that other the Pope, the Quene, the Nobilitie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of Englande, or any other bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye els where, ſhulde or can credite or beleue ſuche wethercockes &amp; dub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blefaced dreamers of myſchefe as Gardener and Boner are. Whoſe wrytynges agaynſt the wycked and vſurped authoritie of theyr louynge father nowe the Romyſhe byſhop, and the vnlawfull mariage of the Quenes mother with kinge Henry the eyght (for ſo they called them both than) ſhall to both theyr perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſhames remayne, whan they are bothe gone to the deuel, excepte they earneſtly repent in tyme, and ratifie agayne that, that they truely wrote than. For yf theyr wrytinges were than falſe, why dyd they (yf it were but for ſhame of the world) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme any falſhed, and cauſe it to be wrytten and printed, excepte they wolde openly ſhewe them ſelues to be the very chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the deuell the father of al lyes &amp; falſhed? Yf thoſe thinges that they wrote than were true, why do they nowe ſo ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly deny them in al theyr wycked do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynges?
<pb facs="tcp:21056:9"/> why do they not nowe ſticke vnto the truth of them eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the death? Vnto death quod he? Naye. whoo there my frende. For bothe they haue alwaye ben moſte tender<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly brought vp, and theyr fleſhe is to fyne, delicate, nyce and to tender to ſuffer ether impriſonment or death for the trueth ſake. Yea they had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther put fyue hundreth to death for affirmyng the truthe (as they haue done many already in theyr tyme) than they wolde either ſticke to it them ſelues, or ſuffer other godlye perſones to lyue, that wolde wyth tothe and nayle ſticke vnto it. But here I wyl let paſſe theſe open ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies both to God, to the truth, and to all true Chriſtianes inhabitinge the realme of Englande, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit them to the vnſearcheable iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of hym, whych knoweth beſte howe to vſe both them, and al other hys creatures to the ſettynge forth of hys glorye, and wyll nowe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede to my matter.</p>
            <p>Whan I had in latin red the no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table confeſſion of the fayth of that excellent learned ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Huldrik Zwin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glius, I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydered (yf it were turned
<pb facs="tcp:21056:9"/> into Englyſhe) that it wolde be both profitable &amp; confortable to a great multitude of my contrey folke, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely to them that are but yongelin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges and weake in knowlege of true religion, wherof ſome perchaunce are in pryſon already for the goſpel ſake, and ſome ſhall hereafter be cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led before the Magiſtrates to gyue a rekening of theyr faith:<note place="margin">A chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought plai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly &amp; open<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to confeſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe with his mouth, the right bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe of his herte. <hi>2.</hi> Cor. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> whervnto yf they ſhalbe requyred, ther is no remedy, but openly and playnly to confeſſe wyth theyr mouthes, what they beleue wyth theyr hertes, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they wil forſake Chriſt and his open truthe, and ſo (whych God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byd) runne into the haſarde of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal damnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Therfore they muſte vnfaynedly ſaye wyth S. Paule: I beleue, and therfore I ſpeake. For vndoutedly, yf euer we loke to be ſaued, the playne and open confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the mouthe muſte neceſſare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye go wyth the ryghte belefe of the herte, thoughe dredful death ſhulde immediatli folowe. Do beleue with the herte iuſtifieth (ſayeth S.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</note> Paul) but to knowledge wyth the mouthe maketh a man ſafe. S. Peter lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe voucheth the ſame, ſayeng:</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21056:10"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.</note>Be ready alwayes to gyue a reke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or an anſwere to euerye man that aſketh you a reaſon of the hope that is in you, and that wyth mek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and feare, hauyng a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            <p>By theſe and ſuche lyke authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and examples of Goddes holye worde it dothe playnly appere: that yf the Magiſtrate or tyrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of any a rekenynge of theyr belefe, they muſte in any wyſe boldly and conſtantly declare it, thoughe they ſe euen death before theyr eyes.</p>
            <p>It is therfore no leſſe but playne hy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pocriſie, diſſimulacion and halfe a denial of the fayth of Chriſte, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue ryghtly wyth the herte, and for fear, flatery, lucre or worldly gayne to ſaye or do the contrarye. God graunt vs all therfore to do as Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the ſonne of Syrack ſayeth:</p>
            <p>Stryue thou for the truthe (ſayeth he) vnto death,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 4.</note> and God ſhall fyght for thee agaynſt thyne enemyes.</p>
            <p>But here one of good knowlege wyl ſaye.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Obiection.</note> Syr I am not yet come vnto that perfeccion to dye for my fayth ſake: neither to forſake my cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey, and therfore I wyl abyde by it
<pb facs="tcp:21056:10"/> and tary here ſtyl.</p>
            <p>I anſwere:<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſwere</note> then I wyl aduyſe thee who ſoeuer thou arte, to make thy rekenyng wyth thy ſelfe before, Examyne thyne owne herte &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyder well: whether thou doeſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faynedly feele in thy ſelfe ſuche a ſtronge &amp; ſtoute ſtomake, that thou canſt be content boldly to confeſſe &amp; byde by thy fayth: and for the truth ſake wyllyngly and gladly forſake father, mother, ſyſter, brother, wyfe chyldren, and al worldly pleaſures, and further ſuffer therfore ſhame, rebuke, loſſe of all thy landes, goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and promocions, forſakyng of thy kynſfolke and frendes, lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, tyrannical tormentes, and finally moſte ſhamefull death: Yf thou (I ſaye) vnfaynedly feeleſt in thy ſelfe ſuche a luſty corage that thou canſt conſtantlye and wyth a ioyful herte do al theſe thynges for the loue of thy Lorde, and for the truthe ſake, than on goddes name ſtande vnto it and abyde all ſharpe ſtormes and tempeſtes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> &amp; God ſhall (as Syrak ſayeth) fyght for thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt thyne enemies. And ſo in al thy greateſt trouble thou ſhalte glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie
<pb facs="tcp:21056:11"/> God.</p>
            <p>But contrarie wyfe yf thou feele in thy ſelfe weakneſſe, and arte af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayed that thou arte not able to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer all theſe thynges, doutynge that thou can not ſtande ſtably in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen confeſſion of thy ryght faythe &amp; beleue, and paciently ſuffer al the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore named tormentes: Than I wil aduyſe the in any wyſe to followe Chriſtes aduertiſement and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 10.</note> ſayeng: wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they perſecute you in one cytie (wherin is vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded village, towne, cuntrey or region) flye vnto an other. For yf thou feeling in thy ſelfe ſuche weak<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe wilt aduenture to tarye ſtyll, than beware of theſe terrible threat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynges of Chriſte, ſayeng: who ſo euer ſhall deny me before men,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 10.</note> him wyl I alſo denye before my father whych is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marc.</hi> 10.</note> Agayne, who ſo euer ſhalbe aſhamed of me &amp; of my wordes in this aduoutrouſe &amp; ſinful generacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: of him alſo ſhal the ſonne of man be aſhamed wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth in the glorye of hys father wyth the holy Angels. Come awaye therfore ſpedely, and preuent theſe great dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gers of denyal of Chriſt, and of hys
<pb facs="tcp:21056:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> knowen truthe.</p>
            <p>But thys my poore and ſymple aduice good brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſyſters tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheth nothynge at al any of vs that are already come awaye for the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel ſake. For (God be prayſed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) we haue obeyed Chriſtes voice both ſpeakynge in S. Iohn &amp; in S. Paule. In S. Iohns Reuelacion thus ſayeth Chriſt:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc,</hi> 18.</note> Come away my people from Babylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ye be not partakers of her ſynnes, that ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue not of her plages. In S. Paul thus ſayeth the Lorde:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor</hi> 6.</note> Come out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amonge them, and ſeperate youre ſelues from them (ſayeth the Lord) and touche none vncleane thynge: ſo wyll I receaue you, and wyl be a father vnto you, and ye ſhalbe my ſonnes and doughters, ſayeth the Lorde almyghtye.</p>
            <p>Loo, theſe two ſcriptures I haue reherſed agayne, both for our ſingu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler comforte, and for the comfortes of al them, that ſhall do the lyke that we haue done by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge awaye. And in wayinge of theſe two afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd ſcriptures I can not but moch reioyſe and prayſe God on oure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, and that for diuers conſydera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions
<pb facs="tcp:21056:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> followynge:</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Fyrſt by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng away we haue declared oure ſelues to be Chriſtes people. For Chriſte ſayeth: come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye my people from Babylon.</p>
            <p>Marke that he calleth the flyers fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ydolatrie hys people. Seyng tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thus flyinge awaye we are accomp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted by this place of ſcripture to be of Chriſtes people, haue we not muche cauſe in our hertes to reioyſe &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie God? I thinke we haue.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Agayne, for that we haue obeyde the Lordes voyce ſayeng: Come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: Come out from amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge them: Separate your ſelues from them: touche none vncleane thynge, we ſhal vndoutedly be partakers of the bleſſynges mencioned in the holye ſcriptures:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. <hi>Leui.</hi> 26.</note> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yf we be partakers of Goddes bleſſynges, it is a plaine aſſurance that God is on our ſyde. Yf God be on our ſyde, who tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can finally preuayle agaynſt vs? Dout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, neither Reyſer, Kinge, Quene tyraunt, deuel, death nor hell.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Further, in commyg awaye we haue declared that we vtterly deteſt and abhorre al Idolatrye, ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon, papiſtrie and falſe worſhippin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge
<pb facs="tcp:21056:12"/> of God, and not to be partakers of them and other abhominacyons, whych nowe ouerflowe that noble realme of England: by reaſon wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of we ſhal and that moſt fortunatly auoyde and eſcape ſuche greate pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as now ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ouer it. For which cauſe let vs dayly more &amp; more ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye to be thanckful vnto the Lorde.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Finally, as we haue obeyed (bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God therfore) thoſe commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementes: Comme awaye: Comme out from amonge them: Separate your ſelues from them: touch no vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clean thynge: So ſhal we be partta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of theſe promeſes followinge, that is: ſo wyl I receaue you: and wyl be a father vnto you: &amp; ye ſhall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be my ſonnes and doughters, ſayth the Lorde almyghtie.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſwete promeſes and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual confortatiues let vs be mynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of both whan we laye vs down to reſt, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ryſe vp agayn. And giue God moſt hertie thanckes both for them, and for that grace that he gaue vs to leaue our countrey, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynges and promocyons and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me awaye.</p>
            <p>But here a papiſt wyl ſaye that
<pb facs="tcp:21056:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> I am out of my witte,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Obiection</note> to ſaye that we are fortunate with commynge awaye, nowe ſuffering greuouſe ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yle, diſpatched of our lyuinges, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken of our kynſfolke, and out of the Quenes fauoure. Thys (wyl he ſaye) is to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me out of Goddes bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng into a warme ſonne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſwere.</note>I anſwere: The fleaſſh and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal reaſon wyl iudge no leſſe. But yf we iudge after the rule of holy ſcripture, it is qwyte contrarie: For all Chriſtes ſcholars muſte ſuffer trouble in thys worlde. As S. Paul affirmeth,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.</note> ſayinge: Al they whyche wyl lyue godly in Chriſt Ieſu ſhal ſuffer perſecucion. Thys exile ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is our croſſe, whych we muſte eſteme to be ſwete vnto vs for Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes ſake,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.</note> becauſe he ſayeth: he that taketh not hys croſſe and foloweth me, is not worthye of me. And: yf a man come to me, and hate not hys father and mother, and wyfe &amp; chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luce.</hi> 14.</note> and brethren and ſyſters, yea and hys owne lyfe alſo, he can not be my diſciple.</p>
            <p>And touchynge our perſecucion and exile let vs patiently beare it. For Chriſt ſuffred muche more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecucion
<pb facs="tcp:21056:13"/> for vs. And was compelled in hys infancie (kynge Herode ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge to deſtroye him) to flye away out of his owne natiue cuntrey into a ſtraunge lande,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2</note> and there to tary a lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge tyme tyl the death of his per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecutour.</p>
            <p>As for the Quenes diſpleaſure towardes vs (though perchaunce ſo me other cauſes are pretended) it is doutles for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel ſake. Therfore let vs ſtrongly beare it, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitte our hole cauſe vnto God, &amp; let hym alone wyth the redreſſe therof, and dayly praye for her true conuerſion vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enbracynge of Chriſtes true religion.</p>
            <p>But concernynge the ſpoyle of your landes, goodes and poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and the lawles robberie of oure ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynges and benefices, let vs glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitte them into the handes of God, and he wyl moſte ſurely (wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſeeth conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t tyme) reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence euery peny to the vttermoſte, other one waye, or els an other: other ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually, or bodely, or both.<note place="margin">Let vs truſt ſurly to Chriſtes, payment.</note> Let vs truſte ſurely to Chriſtes recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacion, whyche promyſeth to vs (I ſaye to vs) repayment, ſayeng:</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21056:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 19</note>Euery one that forſaketh houſe, or brethren, or ſyſters, or father, or mother, or wyfe, or children, or la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de for my names ſake, ſhal receaue an hundreth folde, and ſhall inherite e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtyng lyfe. Lo here Chriſt ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: Euery one. whyche conſydered, than ſaye I, that he dothe not except vs, nether any that hath done as we haue done. For hys promyſe is vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſal.<note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſal.</note> And as the promyſe is vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſal, ſo is alſo the perfourmance therof, yf man continueth faythfull in hys callynge.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 18.</note>Saynt Luke reherſyng thys ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eng of Chriſt, ſayeth thus. Verelye I ſay vnto you: Ther is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hath forſaken houſe, eyther father or mother, eyther brethren or wyfe, or chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (for the kyngdome of god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des ſake) whyche ſhall not receaue muche more in thys worlde, and in the world to come lyfe euerlaſting. As thoughe Chriſt ſhulde thus ſay: No man for my cauſe ſhal ſuffer da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage here, but ſhall enioye muche more againe for it, both in this lyfe, and in the lyfe to come.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marc,</hi> 10.</note>S. Marke telleth Chriſtes tale af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter thys ſorte: Verely I ſaye vnto
<pb facs="tcp:21056:14"/> you: There is no man that hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken houſe, or brethren, or ſyſters, or father, or mother, or wyfe, or chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren, or landes, for my ſake and the goſpels, but he ſhall receaue an hun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dreth folde nowe in this lyfe, houſes and brethren, and ſyſters, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and chyldren, and la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des with perſecucions, and in the worlde to come eternal lyfe.<note place="margin">Hundreth fold.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thys hundrethfolde ſignifyeth a mynde muche better content and ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſfyed with that porcion be it neuer ſo lytel that God ſhall gyue one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes hys fyndyng in hys exyle &amp; aduerſitie, than wyth that great abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>daunce had in tyme of proſperitie.</p>
            <p>Chriſtianes for Goddes glorie forſaking theyr houſes and goodes, for one houſe forſaken ſhalbe many times moſte hertely welcome to ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny godly mennes houses. Yea the faythful ſhal ſo gladlye receaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and charitably intreat them, that they ſhall thynke them ſelues fortu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nate to haue in theyr houſes ſuche ſtraungers and geaſtes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>So thought Symon the Ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner that lodged Peter, &amp; lykewyſe Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius the captayne.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21056:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 16.</note>So were Paulus and Sylas at Philippos moſte gladly take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge wyth godly Lydia the ſeller of purple, whych ſayd vnto them: Yf ye thynke that I beleue on the Lorde, come into myne houſe and a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>byde there. I could here bryng you exemples of Abraham, Iob and Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid, whyche for theyr patient ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng exyle, ſpoyle, and loſſe of lande and cuntrey, were muche more abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dantly enriched of God afterward, than they were before.</p>
            <p>But here my good brethren and ſyſters,<note place="margin">Iouianus &amp; Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinianus.</note> I praye you marke the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of two noble gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the one named Iouianus and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other Vale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinianus, beyng both of the in hygh fauour and authoritie, and were Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pitaynes of a thouſande men a pece vnder Iulianus the Emperoure, whych in the begynnyng profeſſed Chriſt but afterwards forſoke him, and perſecutyng the Chriſtianes be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>came a playne Apoſtata. Thys wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Emperour by a lawe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded al hys men of warre vnder pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of loſynge theyr promocions to do ſacrifice vnto hys falſe Goddes.<note place="margin">In hiſto. Tripar. lib. <hi>7.</hi> ca. <hi>1</hi> Es Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doricut. li. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Iouianus notwythſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng rather
<pb facs="tcp:21056:15"/> than he wolde obey a wycked com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of a wycked Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and ſo denye and ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der the profeſſion of his fayth in Chriſt, cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe vtterly to forſake and departe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hys great promocion. For whyche cauſe Chriſt wel recompenſed hym. For after the worthy cruel death of that wycked Emperour, Iouianus was aduaunſed to be Emperoure nexte after hym.</p>
            <p>So lykewyſe the noble gentelma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Valentinianus beynge a chriſtian folowynge hys maiſter the ſaid wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked Emperour Iulianus whan he wente to the Temple of hys falſe Goddes,<note place="margin">Theodori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cus li. <hi>4.</hi> ca <hi>5.</hi> &amp; Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par. hiſt. li. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>35.</hi>
               </note> was of the heythen Preſte be ſprincled wyth holy water. And beynge greued therwyth, for the ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ale that he bare vnto Chriſte, gaue the preſte a blowe of the eare, &amp; bold<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye ſayde:<note place="margin">So may one righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly ſaye of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly water.</note> that wyth that water he was rather polluted than purged. For whych thynge, he was firſt im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>priſoned, and than exiled and bany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. Neuertheles for hys feruente zeale in gyuynge the heythen preſte a blowe, Chriſt afterwardes wel re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>compenſed hym. For next after the death of the ſayd Emperour Iouia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,
<pb facs="tcp:21056:16"/> was he exalted to be Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of Rome. So is it playne, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for their great loſſes of their ꝓmocions for the profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their fayth ſake, Chriſt euen in thys lyfe recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed eyther of them an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth fold. I coulde brynge mo hiſtories to the confirmacion of this matter, but I wyl for thys tyme content my ſelfe with theſe. But yet one leſſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> derely beloued let euery one of vs learne of S. Paule, and ſaye wyth hym e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from the very herte thus:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 4.</note> I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue learned in what ſo euer ſtate I am therwith to be content. I know howe to be lowe, and I knowe how to excede: Euery where and in all thynges I am inſtructed both to be ful and to be hongrye, both to haue plentie, and to ſuffer nede. I can do all thynges throughe Chriſte that ſtrenghneth me.</p>
            <p>Thus makynge an ende of my longe bablyng wyth you dearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued brethren and ſyſters, I here preſent vnto you the notable confeſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of the fayth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greate learned man Huldrik Zwinglius, whych I haue after my groſſe knowlege la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely tranſlated out of laten for the
<pb facs="tcp:21056:16"/> inſtruccion and comfort of the true Chriſtianes of Englande. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I had tranſlated it within leſſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one leafe of the laſt ende, one of our brethren ſhewed it to me tranſlated already many yeares ago and prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted at Zurik. Whych thynge had al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moſte cauſed me to ſuppreſſe my tranſlacion: had not an other after that tolde me, that of the old tranſla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion ther was but a ſmale nombre printed, &amp; many of them were loſte. In conſyderacion wherof, he aduy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me &amp; that earneſtly to put forth thys my tranſlacion, bothe for the profyte of many of my Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren whych neuer red the former tranſlacion, and alſo for the reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of ſo worthy a confeſſion, and ſo haue I done.</p>
            <p>I haue alſo added thervnto two lytle Epiſtles of myn owne: the one conteynyng my poore and ſymple iudgement concernyng the confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſynnes, howe farre the holye ſcripture wyl beare therwyth. And what I thynke touchynge eare con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nowe reuyued agayne in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande. The other Epiſtle is an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to the demaunde of a godlye
<pb facs="tcp:21056:17"/> lady moſte inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly deſyryng me to declare vnto her y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true meaning of an hard texte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cha of S. Paules Epiſtle to the Hebrues, &amp; alſo what is the ſynne againſt the holy ghoſt, and howe and wherin it differreth from all other ſynnes.</p>
            <p>Theſe thynges wrytten after my rude maner and nowe put forth in printe I beſech you take in good worth, and of your Charitie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre me in youre dayly prayers</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21056:17"/>
            <p>VVe whyche preache the Goſpel in cyties, townes and villages, of chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip O Charles noble Emperour conſecrated &amp; holy appointed to equitie and ryghte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſnes, haue longe deſyrouſly loked-for when a rekenyng of oure fayth, whych both we haue &amp; profeſſe, ſhuld be required of vs. And whyle we ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thus in a redynes, it is ſayd, rather of comon brute, then of any ſure and certayne meſſage or tydynges, that many alredy haue prepared and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the order, ſumme and fourme of their fayth and religion, which they maye ſpedely preſent vnto you. And here are we in great doute and perplexitie, for on the one part y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue of truthe and great deſyre of como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quietnes pricketh vs forwarde to do the ſame our ſelues, that we ſe other do: And on the other ſyde, ſhortneſſe of tyme afrayeth vs, Partlye, for that we muſte do al thynges to haſtely, &amp; paſſe them ouer to lyghtly, becauſe of your great haſte, (for ſo the rumour goeth that you wyl make haſte from thenſe.) And partly, becauſe we whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che are preachers of goddes worde in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21056:18"/> cyties, townes and villages are pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced farther abrode, than we can in ſo ſhorte a tyme aſſemble and take adui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, what were moſte mete to writ vnto your hyghneſſe. Wherfore ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng that we haue alredy ſene the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſion of the fayth of other, yea and alſo the confutacion of their aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries (which neuertheleſſe ſemed to be prepared before any thinge (touching that) was demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of them) I thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght it was not vnmere yf I alſo pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatly without the hynderau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of my contreyfolke ſhulde forthwith declare a reaſon and rekenyng of my fayth. For although other matters require ſofte and eaſy haſte, yet in this thyng quicke ſpede is to be made, leſt (y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter ſlouthfully paſſed ouer) we ſhulde fall in daunger other of ſuſpicious ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, or els of preſumptuouſe negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. Lo therfore (O moſte myghty Emperoure) here I offer vnto youre maieſtye the ſumme of my fayth on this condicion, that I maye alſo wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe therby my ſelfe to commit and ſuffer the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t not only of theſe articles, but alſo of al other whych I haue hertofore at any tyme wrytten, or by the goodnes of God hereafter
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21056:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhal wryt, not to one only, neither yet to a fewe, but to the hole Churche of Chriſt ſo farre as it pronounceth by the rule and inſpiracion of Goddes worde and ſpirite.</p>
            <div n="1" type="article">
               <head>¶The firſt article.</head>
               <p>FYrſt of al I bothe beleue and knowe,<note place="margin">His fayth of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of God.</note> that ther is but one a lonly God, and that he is of nature good, true, almighty, ryghteouſe, wyſe and mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, the maker and gouernour of all thynges viſible &amp; inuiſible. And that the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt are thre perſones, but the Eſſence &amp; ſubſtance of them is ſimple, vnmixte and but one alone. And concerninge the Godhed and names or thre perſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes I agree vtterly in opinion in al thinges wyth the declaracion of the Crede aſwel of <hi>Nicene</hi> as of <hi>Athanaſius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I beleue that the Sonne hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to hym fleſſhe,<note place="margin">His belefe of Chriſt the ſonne of God &amp; the ſon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of man.</note> vnderſtandynge therby, that he hath verely and truly of Mary the vndefyled and perpetual virgine taken to hym the nature of man, yea the hole man, whych conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth of body and ſoule, and that after this maner: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame hole ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:21056:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> is ſo taken into the vnitie of ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or perſone of the ſonne of God,<note place="margin">Of two na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ures in one perſone</note> that man maketh not a proper or ſpecial perſone, but is taken vnto the inſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, indiuiſible, and vnlouſable per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonage of the ſonne of God.<note place="margin">The diſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cte proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties &amp; ope<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rations o the two na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures in Chriſte di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uide not the perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</note> And al be it that both natures, that is the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed and Manhed ſo kepe ſtyl their na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures and properties, that both of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in hym may truely and naturally be knowen and perceaued, yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſſe the diſtincte and ſeueral proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and workinges of natures diuid not the vnitie of perſone. No more than in man the ſoule and body make two perſones. For as thei are of moſt diuers and contrary natures, ſo are they alſo of ſundry properties and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peracions. And yet man whych con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyſteth of them both is not two perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but one: Euen ſo God and Man is one Chriſt: the perpetual ſonne of God from euerlaſtynge, and the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme appointed &amp; deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined. One perſone, one Chriſt, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte God, and perfect Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Not that the one nature is made the other, or that they are mixed, confounded or diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ordred amonge them ſelues, but that either of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abydeth ſtyl in his owne
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21056:19"/> propertie. And yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnitie of perſone by theſe ſondrie properties is not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned. And thus one &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Chriſt touchyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> propertie of his manhed cried as a chylde, grewe &amp; waxed, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocaſed in wyſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gred, thryſted, dyd eat, drynke, ſlepe was hote colde, beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, dyd ſwet, was wounded, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, affrayed, was in heuineſſe, and ſuffred other thinges, whych pertain vnto the payne and punyſhment of ſynne, and yet was he vtterly gyltles and moſte eſtraunged from ſynne it ſelfe. But touchynge the propertie of hys Godhed, he wyth the Father and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt ordreth, goeth thorow, ruleth, ſuſtayneth and nurryſheth all thynges both hyghe &amp; lowe, he lyght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the blynde, reſtoreth the lame, calleth vp the dead, wyth a lytle word throweth downe his enemies, beyng deade he taketh agayne to hym lyfe, he aſcendeth vp to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſendeth downe the holy Ghoſt as his owne ſpirite. And one and the ſame Chriſte abydynge in one perſone of the ſonne of God doth al theſe thynges, albeit they are contrary in nature and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie, ſo that eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe thinges, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che belonge properly to the Godhede,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21056:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> becauſe of the vnitie and perfeccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of perſone, are ſometyme aſcrybed and imputed to the Manhode: and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye, thoſe thynges whych are proper to the Manhode, are ſometyme ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Godhede.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohan.</hi> 3.</note> He ſayd: that he hym ſelfe beynge the ſonne of Man was in heauen, when he had not yet in body aſcended into heauen.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Petre.</hi> 2.</note> Peter alſo ſheweth: that Chriſte ſuffred for vs, when only hys ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>hode could ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. But for vnitie of perſone it is tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye ſayd: bothe that the ſonne of God ſuffred, and that the ſonne of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaue ſynnes. For bothe he whyche in one perſone is the ſonne of God, and the ſonne of Man, touchinge the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of hys manhode, ſuffred: And he whych in one perſone is the ſonne of God, and the ſonne of Man, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge hys Godhed, forgaue ſynnes. So we ſaye: thys man is wyſe, whan notwythſtandynge he conſyſteth aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel of body as of ſoule. And the body is moſte eſtraunged from wyſedom, yea it is a very poiſon and hyndrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of knowlege and vnderſtandynge.</p>
               <p>And agayne, we ſaye: the ſame ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſore cutte and wounded, whan onely the bodye can receaue woundes, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21056:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> not the ſoule. Thus no man ſayeth. Of man there is made two perſones, whan to either partie hys owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie is attributed and applyed. And agayne no man ſayeth: that the natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res are mixte, diſordred and confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, whan of the hole man that is ſayd, whych for the vnitie of perſone pertayneth to the hole, but for the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pertie of the parties belongeth onely vnto one. Paule ſayeth:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.</note> whan I am weake, then am I ſtronge. Who is it that is weake? Paule. who ryghtly is alſo ſtronge? Paule. But is not thys ſayeng contrarye to reaſon, vnſtable and intollerable? No. for Paul is not of one nature, albeit he is but one per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſone. Therfore whan he ſayeth: I am weake, doutleſſe that perſon ſpeaketh whych is Paule, but that that is ſayd, is neither ſpoken nor vnderſtanded of both natures, but only of the weak<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe of the fleſhe. And whan he ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, I am ſtronge: Surely the perſon of Paule ſpeaketh it: but only hys ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite is vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. Euen ſo, the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God is dead: Doutleſſe he (whyche by vnitie and ſingleneſſe of perſone is bothe God and Man) is deade, but that is only touchyng hys manhode.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21056:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> Thus therfore not only I thynke con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cernynge aſwel the Godhead and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſones, as taking to the nature of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſo lykewyſe haue thought al they both olde and newe that are of ryght fayth and belefe. Yea and ſo thynke they alſo that euen nowe acknowlege the truthe vnfaynedly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="article">
               <head>¶The ſeconde Article.</head>
               <p>SEcondarely, I knowe and beleue,<note place="margin">Here fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes free wyll.</note> that thys moſte excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t maieſtie, which is my God, doth frankely and wythout co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtraynt or let appoint and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine of al thynges, ſo that his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſel and determinacion hangeth of no cauſe or occaſion of any creature, for that is the propertie of the maymed wiſedome of man, to iudge and deter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mine by conferrynge and debatynge of natural reaſons, or by exemple go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynge before. But God (whyche from euerlaſtynge vnto for euer &amp; euer w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one only and ſimple lokynge vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on beholdeth al thynges) nedeth no ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>compt,<note place="margin">Goddes prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</note> rekenyng, experience or profe of thynges that are done, but beynge on euery parte wyſe, prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, good &amp;c. hath frankly determyned and ſet an order in al thynges. For hys owne
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21056:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> are al thynges that are. Hereof it is, that all be it wyttingly and aduiſedly he in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begynnyng wolde make ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes creation.</note> whych he knewe perfectly wolde fal, yet neuertheleſſe wolde aſwell deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myne, to cloth hys ſonne wyth mans nature, to repayre and reſtore againe the fall: wherby hys goodnes on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry parte doth appere.<note place="margin">In Goddes goodnes is conteyned mercy &amp; righteou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> In whych good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes is compriſed both hys mercy and ryghteouſnes. His ryghteouſnes he put forth, whan he caſt the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſours out of the pleaſaunt manſions of Paradyſe: whan he tyed them in the priſon of mannes myſery, and fet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tered them in the chaynes of ſyckneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and whan he layed the lawe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, whych (albeit it was holy) they could neuer of theyr owne power ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyl. For here man beynge a dubble wretch learned, not only hys body to haue fallen into myſery, but alſo his mynde for fear of the lawe tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed to be tormented. For whan after the ſpirite he ſawe that the lawe was holye,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Roma.</hi> 7.</note> ryghteous and the meſſenger of Goddes mynde and wyll, as ſhe whych co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded nothyng but that-that ryghte requyred, but yet alſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge that by dedes he coulde not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyll
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21056:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> the mynd of the lawe, he in hys owne iudgement condempned (the hope of attaynyng felicitie caſt awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye) goyng awaye deſperate from the ſight of God, remembred nothing but that he ſhulde ſuffer the payne of eternal tormentes. Thus farre was Gods ryghteouſnes made open.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mercy.</note>After thys whan the tyme ſhulde come to vtter hys goodnes, which fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begynnyng he appointed to ſhew as well as ryghteouſnes,<note place="margin">Chriſtes in carnation</note> he ſent hys ſonne to take to hym oure nature on euery parte, except that that is diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and redy to ſynne, that he made a brother and lyke vnto vs, myght be a mediator, whych for vs by offering hys innocent body vnto death, might ſatiſfye Goddes moſt vpryght iuſtice, whych behoued to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue holy, pure &amp; vncorrupt aſwel as hys goodneſſe, that the worlde myght be throughlye aſſured both of the recompenſacion &amp; ſatiſfyeng of hys ryghteouſnes, and of hys preſent mercy to be offered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. For ſeyng he hath to vs and for vs geuen hys owne ſonne,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Roma.</hi> 8.</note> howe ſhall he not to vs gyue al thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges with hym and for hym? what is it that we may not promyſe to our ſelues of him whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21056:22"/> hath let downe, abaſed and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled him ſelf hyther, to be not only ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vnto vs, but alſo to be holly &amp; fully our owne? who can maruel ynough at the ineſtimable rycheſſe and fauor of Goddes goodnes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohan.</hi> 3. 1. <hi>Iohan.</hi> 4</note> wherby he hath ſo loued the world, that is, mankynd, to gyue his owne ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyfe of it?</p>
               <p>Theſe lyuely fountaynes &amp; ſwete vaynes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel I thynke are the only and alone medicine of the ſycke ſoule,<note place="margin">The only medicyn of the ſyck ſowle.</note> wherby ſhe is reſtored bothe to God &amp; to her owne ſelfe. For nothing can aſſure her of Goddes fauour, but God hym ſelfe. And he ſo lyberally, ſo abundauntly and ſo prudently hathe powred hys louynge kyndnes hollye vpon vs, that nowe he hath lefte no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge behynde that we can deſyre, onleſſe any durſt requyre any thinge more then enough, and aboue the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerflowynge habundaunce.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="article">
               <head>¶The thyrde Article.</head>
               <p>THyrdlye, I knowe ther is no nother Sacrifice of pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynge ſynne, but Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</note> (for Paule truly was not crucifyed for vs:) &amp; that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21056:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> ther is none ſo ſure and vndoutefull pledge of Goddes goodnes &amp; mercye as is Chriſt (for ther is nothynge ſo ſure as God,<note place="margin">Chriſt is the only waye to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>conciliati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on &amp; feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite. Acte. <hi>4.</hi> Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes &amp; pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng vnto Sainctes is here diſpat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched. <hi>1.</hi> Timo. <hi>2</hi> The electe are on this condition choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that by the ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne they myght be ſaued.</note> which affirmeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame) and that vnder the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ther is none other name but the name of Ieſus Chriſt, wherby we muſte be ſaued.</p>
               <p>Here therfore (concernynge the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynynge of Goddes goodnes &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) are refuſed as wel the iuſtificacion and ſatiſfaccion of our workes, as the merites, deſeruynges, prayers, and interceſſions of all ſaintes, whether they be in earth, or in heauen. For here is but that one alonly mediator betwixte God and man, the God and man Ieſus Chriſt. And Goddes elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion abydeth ſtedfaſt &amp; ſure, for thoſe that he hath choſen before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> makinge of the worlde, he hath ſo choſen them, that he myght choſe them out to hym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe by hys ſonne. For as he is gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel and mercyful, ſo is he holy &amp; rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous. Al hys workes therfore reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of mercy &amp; ryghteouſnes. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ryghtly his eleccion ſmelleth of them both. Of hys goodnes it was to haue choſen whome he wolde, but it was of ryghteouſnes to purchaſe and ioyne to hym ſelfe them that are cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21056:23"/> through hys ſonne made a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to recompence Goddes ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes for vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="article">
               <head>¶The fourth Article.</head>
               <p>FOurthly, I knowe that that great graundfathers father, our fyrſt father Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through ſelfe loue, by the ſubtyle ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, wycked temptacion and enuious cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel of the deuel, was allured to thys pointe, to couet to be made lyke vnto God. And when he had committed that ſynne, he taſted of the forbydden and moſte daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous frute,<note place="margin">Of origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſynne.</note> wherby he fel into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faute and gyltineſſe of moſt horrible death and dampnacion, made therby the ſtubburne aduerſarie and enemye of hys God. Wherfore wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God myght of equitie and ryght haue vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed hym, yet beyng moſte graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe Lorde vnto him, he chaunged his euerlaſtynge payne and punyſhment into a ſtate, that is, to make hym a bond ſeruaunt, whome he myght ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue worthelye punyſhed wyth euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng death and vtter deſtruccion.</p>
               <p>For aſmuch than, as neither he, nor
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21056:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> yet any that is borne of hym can take awaye thys ſtate and condicion of bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dage (for a bondman can not but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get another bond ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) he hath by the deadly taſtyng of the forbydde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> frute,<note place="margin">They are called bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that are ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued, whan of right they might haue bene kylled by their ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers.</note> keſt all hys poſteritie into bondage. Nowe therfore touchynge original ſynne I thynke thus:</p>
               <p>That is truly called ſynne, whych is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe: for where no lawe is, there is no tranſgreſſion. And where no tranſgreſſion is, there is no ſynne, as ſynne is properlye ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, that is, ſo far as ſynne is a dede, a faute, an acte or offence. Therfore I acknowlege that our fyrſt father ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a ſinne, that is ſinne in dede, that is to ſay, an acte a faute, and a deteſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble thynge. But they that are borne of hym haue not ſynned after that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. For whyche of vs haue bytten wyth our teeth and eaten the forbyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den frute in Paradice? Wherfore wil we nyl we, we are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to graunt that original ſynne as it is in the chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren of Adam, is not properly ſynne, as it is nowe declared, for properly it is not an acte or dede co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the lawe. But it may properly be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, a byrthſore, a naturall ſyckneſſe &amp;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21056:24"/> diſeaſe, and alſo it may be called a ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful ſtate and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicion. A diſeaſe it is, for as he of ſelf loue fel, ſo we alſo fal It is alſo a ſynful ſtate or condicion: for lyke as he by his ſynne was made bond and ſubiecte to death, ſo we alſo are borne bond, the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of wrath, and ſubiecte to death. Al be it I paſſe nothynge yf thys diſeaſe and condici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on after Paules maner be called ſyn, yea it is ſuche a ſynne, that who ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer are borne in it are the enemies &amp; aduerſaries of God: for hither the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful ſtate of our byrth draweth vs, and not the actual co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mittynge of offence, excepte ſo farre as oure fyrſt parent hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted it once. Therfore the very cauſe of enmitie &amp; death is the ſynne and offente committed of Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Synne is the cauſe of mannes miſerie.</note> and that is verely ſynne. But this ſyn whych cleaueth to vs in our concepci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is verely a natural diſeaſe &amp; a ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſtate, yea a neceſſitie of dyenge. Notwythſtandyng that neuer ſhulde haue ben by byrth onely, had not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence fyrſt defyled the byrth. Synne therfore is the cauſe of mannes myſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry, and not the byrth. But of byrth it is none otherwiſe, than of it that fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loweth of the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayne and principall
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21056:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> cauſe. The confirmacion of this ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tence is grounded both vpon authori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie and exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Roman.</hi> 5.</note> Paule ſpeaketh thus: Yf by the ſynne of one,<note place="margin">Autoritie</note> death reygned by the meanes of one: muche more they (whyche receyue abundaunce of grace, and of the gyfte of ryghteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) ſhal raigne in lyfe by the meanes of one, that is to ſaye, Ieſus Chriſt. Here we ſe that ſynne is properly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. for this one, is Adam, throughe whoſe fall death ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth ouer our nec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes. Agayne the ſame Paule ſayeth: All haue ſynned and haue nede of the glorie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Roman.</hi> 3.</note> that is, the goodnes &amp; lybera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytie of God. Here ſynne is taken for the diſeaſe, ſtate and byrth, that we al are ſayd to ſynne, yea before we are powred out into thys lyght, that is, we are in the ſtate and condicion of ſynne and death, yea before we ſynne in acte or dede, whyche ſentence vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoydably is agayne ſtrengthned by theſe wordes:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Roman.</hi> 5.</note> Neuertheleſſe death raigned from Adam to Moſes, euen ouer them alſo which had not ſynned wyth lyke tranſgreſſion as dyd Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Loo, death is vpon vs, albeit we haue not ſynned lyke as Adam dyd. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore? For he ſynned in dede, but ſeyng
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21056:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> we haue not ſynned after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner, why dothe death deuoure vs? For he is dead becauſe of ſynne, and beynge dead, that is, iudged to death, he hath begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. Therfore we alſo dye, but thorowe hys faute, and by our owne ſynfull ſtate and diſeaſe, or yf thou wylt, by ſynne, but take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnproperly.<note place="margin">Exemple. The ſtate ſpri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gheth of the faw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te.</note> The exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple is ſuche: one take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> priſoner in battel, by his vntruth, diſloyaltie &amp; ennemitie hath well deſerued to be a bondma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. They that ar borne of him, that is, the bondmannes children are made bond, not by faute, acte or offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce on theyr behalfe, but by ſtate &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicion, whych followed the faute: for theyr father of whome they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, had deſerued that by offence. The chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but the punyſhment &amp; penaltie of the offence, that is, the ſtate or condicion, the bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and priſon. Yf ye luſt to cal theſe thynges offence, becauſe they are exe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuted and miniſtred for offence, I for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>byd you not. To be ſhort.</p>
               <p>I acknowledge this originall ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne by condicyon &amp; infeccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſpring in al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which are begotten through the affectyon of man and woman.</p>
               <p>And I knowe:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.</note> that we are by nature
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21056:26"/> the chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of wrath: but thorow gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, whych by the ſecond Adam Chriſt hath reſtored the fall, I dowt not to be receyued amonge the chyldren of God, and that after thys maner that foloweth:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="article">
               <head>¶The .v. Article.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">It is raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhnes to condempne infantes dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eng with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>owt bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tym of wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter.</note>FYftly. Doutleſſe thys is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: Yf in Chriſt the ſeconde Adam we are reſtored vnto lyfe, lyke as in the fyrſt Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are gyuen ouer to death, than do we raſhly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempne the chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren borne to chriſten parentes, yea and the chyldren of the heythen alſo. For yf Adam by ſynnynge could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye all mankynde, and Chriſte by dyeng hath not quickened and rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med all mankynde fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the great my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery brought in by hym, then is not lyke the ſaluacion reſtored by Chriſt, and ſo (whych God forbyd) thys ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is not true:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>15.</hi> He wyll not diffine of the infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of the heythen.</note> As in Adam al dye, ſo in Chriſt are al reſtored to lyfe.</p>
               <p>But howe ſo euer men determine of the infantes of the heythen, thys certaynly we affirme, becauſe of the power of ſaluacion perfourmed by
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21056:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> Chriſt, that they raſhly gyue ſentence wythout reaſonable cauſe, that iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth them to the euerlaſtynge curſe, partlye, for the ſayd cauſe of reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion by Chriſt, and partly, for the free eleccion of God, whych foloweth not fayth, but fayth it, wherof I wyl ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke more in the article folowyng. For they whyche are choſen from euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, doutleſſe are choſen before they haue fayth. Therfore they whych for lacke of age haue not fayth, ought not vnaduiſedly to be condempned of vs. For albeit they haue it not yet, yet goddes eleccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is hyd from vs, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yf they be electe, we iudge to haſtelye of thynges to vs vnknowen.</p>
               <p>Neuertheleſſe touchynge the infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of Chriſtianes we diffine other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe, that is to ſaye:<note place="margin">He diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyth of the infantes of chriſtianes</note> that ſo many as are the infantes of Chriſtianes are of the congregacion of Goddes people, and partes &amp; membres of his church, whych we proue of thys wyſe: By the wytneſſes almoſte of al the prophetes it is promyſed that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heythe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhulde be gathered together to the churche of Goddes people. And Chriſt hym ſelfe ſayeth: Many ſhall come from the Eaſte and from the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21056:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> Weſt and ſhal ſytte wyth Abraham, Iſaac and Iacob in the kyngdome of heauen.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 8. <hi>Marc.</hi> 16.</note> And: Go ye into al the world and preache. &amp;c. But to the churche of the Iewes their infantes perteyned aſwel as the Iewes them ſelues.</p>
               <p>Therfore no leſſe pertayne our infan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes vnto the churche of Chriſt, than in tyme paſt the infantes of the Iewes. For yf it were otherwyſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gene.</hi> 17.</note> then were not the promyſe perfourmed and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifyed: for than we ſhulde not equally ſytte with Abraham in Goddes king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome. Doutleſſe he was nombred to the church wyth them, whych alſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſhe were borne of hym. But yf our infantes be not ſo nombred wyth theyr parentes, as were the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantes of the Iewes, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were Chriſt not indifferent, but parcial and enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous towarde vs, denying to vs that, that he had gyuen to them of olde. whych were to muche wyckednes to affirme. For otherwyſe al the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies concernyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> callyng of the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyls ſhulde be made of none effecte. Therfore, for aſmuche as the infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of the Chriſtianes are aſwel of the vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſible church of Chriſt, as are theyr pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes or other that be of age, it is eui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21056:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> that they are aſwel of theyr nom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e we iudge elect, as are theyr parentes. For thys cauſe it is, that I iudge them to do wyckedlye and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly, whyche appoint to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnacyon the infantes of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſeyng that ſo many playne wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of ſcripture affirme the contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye. Which ſhewe that the church of the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyles ſhall not nowe be equall, but much mor large, than the church of the Iewes. All which thynges ſhal nowe be made playne, when we ſhall ſhewe our fayth concernyng the Churche</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="article">
               <head>¶The .vi. Article.</head>
               <p>SYxtlye, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng the church, thus we thynke:<note place="margin">Of the church of the electe.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Church in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures is diuerſly take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Fyrſt it is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for thoſe choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyl of God are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to eternal lyfe. Of whyche Paule ſpeaketh, ſayeng:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.5.</note> that ſhe hath neither wrynkle nor ſpotte. Thys Church is knowen only vnto God. For he only (after the worde of Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon) hath knowen the hertes of the chyldren of men. But neuertheleſſe,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 8.</note>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21056:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> they that are membres of thys chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che knowe verely that they themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues are electe, and are membres of thys fyrſt Churche, becauſe they haue fayth in Chriſt. But they know none other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres therof beſyde themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, for ſo is it wrytten in the acres of the Apoſtles:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 13.</note> And they beleued as ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny as were ordeined to eternal lyfe. Therfore they that beleue are ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to eternal lyfe. But who truly be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leueth, no man knoweth but he that beleueth.<note place="margin">Ephe. <hi>1.2. 2.</hi> Cor. <hi>1.11</hi> The felici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of fayth is to knowe that he is the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toure of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal lyfe.</note> He therfore nowe is ſure that he is the choſen of God. For he (after the worde of the Apoſtle) hathe the earneſt of the ſpirite, wherwith he beyng diſpouſed and ſealed, know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth hym ſelfe to be made, not bond, but verely free, and the ſonne of the familie. For that ſpirite can not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue. Whych, yf he beare recorde vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs &amp; certifyeth our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences, that God is oure father, &amp; that we beynge ſure and wythout feare do cal hym fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, not doutyng but that we ſhal go vnto the euerlaſtyng inheritaunce, than is it certayne that the ſpirite of of the ſonne of God is powred into oure hertes. It is certayne therfore that he is electe whych is ſo ſurely by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21056:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> faith perſwaded. For they that beleue are ordeyned to eternall lyfe.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 13.</note> But many in times paſt were, and many nowe are choſen, whych yet haue no fayth. The bleſſed mother of God,</p>
               <p>Iohn and Paule whyle they were yet but infantes and lytleones were they not electe? &amp; that before the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world? but thys they kne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we not in their i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy nother by fayth nor reuelacyon. Mathew, Zacheus, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righth a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thefe, &amp; Magdale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were they not alſo electe before the world was made? and yet they knewe not that, tyl they were lyghtned by the ſpirite, and drawen of the father vnto Chriſt Hereof therfore it maye be gathered,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ionh.</hi> 6.</note> that this fyrſt churche is knowen on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye vnto God, and that they only whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che haue a ſure and an vnſhake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fayth knowe them ſelues to be membres of thys churche.</p>
               <p>Agayne the Churche is taken vni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſally for al that are rekened vnder the name of Chriſt, that is,<note place="margin">Of the vne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſall &amp; ſenſible Churche.</note> whych ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue gyuen theyr names to Chriſt. Of which a great ſort acknowlege Chriſt ſenſibly by confeſſion of fayth, &amp; vſe of Sacramentes, and yet in theyr her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes other they abhorre hym, or els
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21056:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> knowe him not. Therfore we thinke, that ſo many as acknowledge the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of Chriſt,<note place="margin">In thys church aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel as the good are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyned.</note> are of that Church. So was Iudas of the church of Chriſte, &amp; al they that ſtept backe from Chriſt. For of the Apoſtles Iudas was aſwel thought to be of the churche of Chriſt, as Peter or Iohn, whan he was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge leſſe. But Chriſt knewe who was hys, and who was the deuelles. Of thys knowen and ſenſible church (albeit it agree not in thys worlde) are al that with mouth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe Chriſt, although there be many reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes amonge them.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.</note> For Chriſt payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth out thys church by a proper para<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bel of ten virgins, wherof fyue were wyſe, and fyue folyſhe. Thys churche alſo ſomtyme is called electe, albeit it is not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt church, whych is wyth out ſpotte. but lyke as by the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of men it is Goddes church for the ſenſible confeſſion of fayth, ſo by the ſame reaſon it is called electe. For we iudge them both faythful and cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen, whyche gyue theyr names to Chriſt.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.</note> So ſpake Peter, ſayeng: To the electe whych are ſcattered thorow Pontus. &amp;c. where by the name of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecte he vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth al them whych
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21056:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> were of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacions, to the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he wrote, and not them only whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che properly are choſen of the Lorde. For as they were vnknowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, ſo could he not wryte vnto them.</p>
               <p>Fynally, the Churche is taken for euery partyculer aſſemble, company and congregacion of thys vniuerſal &amp; ſenſible church, as: The church of Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me, the Churche of Auſbrough. The Church of Lyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. There are alſo other maner of takynges of the Churche, whych I wyl paſſe ouer wyth ſylence at thys tyme.</p>
               <p>But here I beleue that ther is one Church of them, whyche haue the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me holy ſpirite that certifyeth them, that they are the true chyldren of the houſholde of God, and theſe are the fyrſt frutes of churches. That church I beleue verely can not erre, namely in thoſe chefe foundacions of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayth, wherin the chefe pointe of true religi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on conſyſteth.</p>
               <p>I beleue alſo that the vniuerſal &amp; ſenſible congregacion is one church, ſo longe as it holdeth thys true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of fayth, wherof it is ſayde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redy. And I beleue that al they are of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche, whyche gyue theyr names
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21056:30"/> to it accordynge to the rule and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe of Goddes worde. I beleue alſo that the infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes Iſaac, Iacob, Iudas and all that were of the ſede of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, &amp; alſo thoſe chyldren whoſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes in the begynnyng of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che at the preachinge of the Apoſtles came to take parte wyth Chriſte, are of thys Church. For yf Iſaac and the reſidue had not bene therof, they had not receyued the badge of the church. Seyng therfor they were of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, the infantes and chyldren of the primatiue churche were alſo therof. And for that cauſe I beleue &amp; knowe that they were marked wyth the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Baptyme.<note place="margin">The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers &amp; mothers, godfathers &amp; god mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers &amp; the churche it ſelfe ackno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wledge their infan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes to be of the church</note> by the recepte whereof, they were rekened to be of the nombre of the Churche. For ſo the very infantes acknowlege before the receyuynge of Baptyme by the mouthes of theyr parentes, and of theyr godfathers and godmothers when they are offered to the churche, yea rather becauſe the promyſe offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them whyche is made no leſſe vnto oure infantes, but muche lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and more often than to the infan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21056:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the olde Hebrewes.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the foundacions of bapty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge infantes and commendynge them to the churche, agaynſt whych al the craftye inuencions and ſubtyll deuices of the Catabaptiſtes can do no thynge. For not only they that beleue are to be baptyſed, but alſo they that acknowlege, and they that are of the churche by the promyſes of Goddes worde. For otherwyſe vtterly none of the Apoſtles ſhulde haue baptyſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man or woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe they were not throughly aſſured of the fayth of them that confeſſed and gaue theyr names.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 8.5.</note> For Symon the iuggler and enchaunter, Ananias, Saphiras and Iudas the traytoure wyth many mo were baptyſed, whan they gaue theyr names to be chriſtianes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.</note> and yet they had no fayth. Contrarywyſe Iſaac beynge an infant was circumciſed, whan he profered not hys name nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beleued, but the promyſe gaue the name. Then, ſeynge that our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantes are in the ſame ſtate that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wes chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were, the promyſe both prefereth the name &amp; acknowlegeth
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21056:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> them to pertayn to our church. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore baptyme (we ſpeake of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of baptyme) as verely as Circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciſion requyreth nothynge but one of theſe, that is, other confeſſion or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferynge of the name: or els the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt or promyſe. Al whych thynges ſhalbe made more euidente by theſe that folowe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="article">
               <head>¶The ſeuenth Article.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes geue not grace.</note>SEue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th. I beleue, yea I know. y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al Sacramentes are ſo farre of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gyuyng of grace, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they do not ſo muche as brynge or miniſtre it. In whych aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion perchaunce (O moſte myghtye Emperour) I ſhalbe thought to mala<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perte. But thus faſt ſtandeth my iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement. For grace as it is wroughte and gyuen to vs of Goddes ſpirite (I ſpeake after the facyon of latyn, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I vſe thys worde grace for forgeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſynnes mercy and free bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte) ſo dothe that gyfte pearce, entre and attayne to our only ſpirite. But a guyde or chariote is not nedful to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite. For the ſpirite is a power and cariage wherby al thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges are caried,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21056:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> neither haue we redde at any tyme in the holye ſcriptures, that ſenſible thynges (as Sacramentes are) could certaynly brynge wyth them the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite. But yf at any tyme ſenſible thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges haue bene caried wyth the ſpirit, then it was the ſpirite that caryed, &amp; not the ſenſible thynges.</p>
               <p>So when the veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wynd was brought,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acte.</hi> 2.</note> by the power of the wynde tongues were alſo brought, but the wynd was not brought by the power of tongwes.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nume.</hi> 11.</note> So the wynd brought the quales, and caried awaye the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtes, but no quayles or locuſtes at any tyme haue bene ſo ſwyfte to carie the wynde.</p>
               <p>So whan the wynd beyng ſo great that it was albe to take away moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes, paſſed by Elias,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 19. <hi>Iohan.</hi> 3.</note> yet the Lorde was not caryed by the wynd. To by ſhorte: the wynd bloweth wher it wyll, that is, the wynd bloweth ſo as his nature is, and thou truly heareſt the voyce of it, but knoweſt not from whence it came, or where it ſtayeth. So is euery one that is borne of the ſpirite, that is, ys lyghtned and dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen inuiſibly, and inſenſybly. Truth hath ſpoken theſe thinges, therfor the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21056:32"/> grace of the ſpirite nether is brought wyth that dyppinge in the water, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wyth that bytte or drawght, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wyth that anoyntinge. For if it were ſo, than it myght be knowen, howe, wher, wherwith, by whom, &amp; into whom the ſpirit were brought. For if the preſent effecte &amp; ſtrength of grace were tyed vnto the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wither they are brought, al thinges are gracyouſly wrought. And wher they are not miniſtred nor applied, al thinges are infeblyſſhed, that is, than were all they graceleſſe whych had not receaued the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes al be it they be electe and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.</note> whyche election is by the grace of God in Chriſte. Nether is there cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe, why the diuynes ſhulde alledge Materia or ſubiectum, the matter or ſubiecte, for that the order and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſicyon of it is before required, that is, that the grace of baptyme or of thankeſgyuyng (for ſo they ſpeake) maye be gyuen to hym, that is fyrſte prepared thervnto. For he whych (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theyr mynde) receyueth this grace by the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, other prepareth hys ſelfe thervnto,<note place="margin">An argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> or els he is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the ſpirite. Yf he prepare hym
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21056:32"/> ſelfe, then haue we alſo ſome power of our ſelues, and ſo the preuentynge grace is nothyng. Yf he be prepared of the ſpirite to the recepte of grace, than I aſke: whether y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alſo be done by the Sacrament as a guyde:<note place="margin">A queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> or without the ſacrement. If by the meanes of the ſacramente, than by the ſacrament man is prepared vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſacramente: And ſo the proceſſe ſhalbe endleſſe, for alwaye the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhalbe required to the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the Sacrament. But if wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Sacrament we are prepared to the recept of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal grace, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite is preſent by hys boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous liberalitie before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and lykewyſe grace is there alredy preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t be brought.<note place="margin">Sacremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes are wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſes wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>with we witneſſe to the church that we haue recey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued the gra &amp; mercy of God</note> Of whych thynges thys is gathered, (whyche wyllyngly and gladly I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe in the ryght vſe of ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes) that the Sacramentes are gyuen for an ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wytneſſe of that grace, whych fyrſt is preſent to euery faythfull par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticuler man.</p>
               <p>So is baptyme before the congregaci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on gyuen to hym, whych before he re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaue it other hath confeſſed the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of Chriſt, or els hathe the worde
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21056:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> of promiſe, wherby it is knowen, wen that he pertayneth to the churth For thys cauſe it is, that when we ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptyſe one of lawful age, we fyrſt aſke hym whether he beleue. And yf he an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwere yea: than in concluſion he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaueth baptyme. Therfore fayth is confeſſed to be preſent, before he recey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue baptyme, and ſo fayth is not gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the recepte of baptyme.</p>
               <p>But yf an infant be offred to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is aſked: whether the chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des parentes offer it to be baptyſed. And whan it is anſwered by the wyt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſes that they wolde haue it bapty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by &amp; by the infant is baptiſed.</p>
               <p>And here the promyſe of God we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t before, that he aſwel eſtemeth our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantes to be of the church, as were the chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Hebrues. For wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they whych are of the churche offer them, than the infante is baptyſed by thys lawe, that for aſmuche as it is borne of chriſtianes, it is by Goddes promy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe reputed and taken amonge the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bres of the Churche. Therfore by bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyme the churche openly receaueth him, which before is receyued by gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce. So than, baptyme bryngeth not grace, but wytneſſeth to the churche,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21056:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> that grace is alredy gyuen to hym, to whome baptyme is miniſtred.</p>
               <p>I beleue therfore O Emperoure, that a Sacrament is a ſygne of an ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye thynge, that is,<note place="margin">What a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is</note> of grace gyuen al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redy. I beleue that it is a viſible figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re or fourme, of an inuiſible grace. whyche by the fre gyfte of God is mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred and gyuen.<note place="margin">Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment af a thing done by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite.</note> And that it is a vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſible example whych neuertheleſſe de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clareth almoſte a certayne conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie, proporcion or agremente of a thynge done by the ſpirite. Moreouer I beleue that a Sacramente is an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen wytneſſe of grace gyuen: As wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are baptyſed, the body is waſſhed wyth a moſte pure Element: but ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by is ſygnifyed, that we thorowe the grace of Goddes goodnes are choſen into the company of the churche and people of God, wherin we oughte to lyue holely, ryghteouſly and godlye, for ſo Paule expoundeth the miſtery.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.</note> Therfore he whych receaueth bapty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me wytneſſeth therby hymſelfe to be of Goddes churche, whyche worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth here God in ſoundneſſe of faith and purenes of lyfe. And for that cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe the ſacramentes,<note place="margin">Awſten vpon Iohn</note> whych are holye Ceremonies (for the worde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21056:34"/> the Element and it is made a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) are deuoutly to be reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>treaty.</hi> 80</note> that is, to be had in price &amp; eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macion, and reuerentlye to be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred &amp; vſed. For albeit they can not pardone vs nor releaſe vs of our ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, yet vyſiblye they ioyne vs to the churche, whych fyrſte were inuiſibly by the grace of Eleccion receyued in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the ſame, whych thynge ſeyng that in the miniſtracion of them it is toge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther pronounced and publyſhed wyth the wordes of Goddes promyſe, it is wyth muche deuocio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be had in eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macion. For yf we thynke otherwyſe of the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, namely that they beyng applied outwardly do purge &amp; clenſe inwardly, then playnly Iew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yſhnes were come home agayne, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che wyth diuerſe waſſhynges, oynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, offerynges, ſacrifyces and meates beleued that theyr ſynnes were purged, and that grace by them were as it were purchaſed &amp; bought. Whych thynge neuertheleſſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, and ſpecially Eſay and Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye dyd alwaye moſte conſtantlye wyth ſharpe wordes ſhake vp, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge that the promyſes and benefit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes are gyuen by the free liberalite of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21056:34"/> God, and not for the regarde of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, merites or outward ceremonies</p>
               <p>I beleue alſo that the Catabapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes denyeng baptyme to the infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of chriſten men, do moſte ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully erre, not only therin, but alſo in many other thynges, wherof nowe is no tyme to ſpeake. And to beware and exchue whether ye wyll the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhneſſe or malyce of them, throughe the helpe of God not wythout peryl I both taught &amp; wrote fyrſte agaynſt them, that nowe throughe hys good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes that infeccion amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſlackt, ceaſſed, relinquyſhed &amp; lefte of, ſo farre is it of that I other haue receyued, taught, or defended any thynge of thys ſedicious ſecte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="article">
               <head>¶The eyght Article.</head>
               <p>EYght, I beleue that in the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Supper of tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes gyuing the very body of Chriſt is pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent wyth the eye,<note place="margin">Of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſupper of the Lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de.</note> contempla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion and beholdyng of fayth: that is, that they whyche gyue than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to the Lorde for the benefyte gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to vs in hys ſonne, acknowlege hym to haue taken to hym very fleſh,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21056:35"/> in it verely to haue ſuffred, and vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to haue waſſhed awaye our ſynnes in hys bloude, and ſo al the thynges done by Chriſt to be made to them in the beholdyng of fayth as it were pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
               <p>But that Chriſtes natural body by ſubſtaunce &amp; really, that is, that hys natural bodye other is preſent in the Supper, or chued in oure mouthes &amp; wyth our teeth, as the Papiſtes and certayne that loke backe vnto the pot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of Egypte ſhewe and wryte, that truely we do not only denye, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly affirme to be an errour, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is contrary to Goddes worde.</p>
               <p>Whych thynge O Emperour, by god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des helpe I ſhal in fewe wordes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke as playne and euident to your ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ieſtie, as is the ſunne. Fyrſt by bryng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynge notable and godly authorities of holy ſcripture. Then wyth argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes taken out of them as it were wyth great peces of ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce encoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teryng in battel againſt our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. And fynally, in ſhewing that the olde doctours &amp; diuines were of oure mynde, and ſtande fully wyth vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A prayer</note>In the meane whyle come O thou holy ſpirite the creatour, be preſent &amp;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21056:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> lyghten the myndes of thyne, fyl with grace and lyght the breaſtes whyche thou haſte made.</p>
               <p>Fyrſt Chriſt him ſelfe the mouth and wyſedome of God ſayeth thus:</p>
               <p>You ſhall alwaye haue poore folke wyth you,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.</note> but me ſhall ye not alwaye haue. Lo here the only preſence of his body is denyed. For accordyng to his Godhede he is alwaye preſent. For ſo is he alwayes euerye where, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to an other worde of hys: I wyl (ſayeth he) be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you vntil the worldes ende. That is, touchyng hys Godhed,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.</note> power, and goodnes.</p>
               <p>Wyth vs in declaryng thys place agreeth S. Aug,<note place="margin">Awſten vpon Iohns goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel the <hi>50</hi> treaty.</note> vpon Iohns Goſpel the .l. treatye.</p>
               <p>Neyther is there cauſe why oure aduerſaries ſhulde alledge: that Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes manhed is, wherſoeuer is hys Godhed, otherwyſe the perſon is diui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded. For that allegyng ſhulde take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye the very manhed of Chriſt. For nothing but God can be euery wher.</p>
               <p>And the manhed to be in one pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, but the Godhed to be euery where doth not diuide the perſone, no more then the ſonne takynge to hym man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed, diuideth the vnitie of ſubſtance.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21056:36"/> But marke thys well. It ſhulde ſeme rather to diuide the vnitie of ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (but yet it dothe not) whyle one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone taketh to hym a creature, which the other two perſones take not to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at all: than is, to diuide the perſone, the manhed to be in one place, but the Godhed to by euery where. For we maye alſo ſe in creatures. That the bodyes are tyed to one place only, but the power and vertue of them ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth farre abrode. As appereth by two examples folowynge.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne.</note>The ſunne is bodely placed but in one place: but hys power and vertue worketh in al places of thys worlde.</p>
               <p>Mannes mynde alſo ſurmoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth euen the very ſtarres and pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the very helles,<note place="margin">Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes mynd.</note> and yet the body is but in one place only.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 16.</note>Chriſte alſo ſayeth thus: Agayne I leaue the worlde and go to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Lo, here is a worde of forſaking, as before ther was a word of hauing: becauſe our aduerſaries ſhal not be a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble to ſaye:<note place="margin">A Popiſch gloſe.</note> we haue him not here viſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blie. For whan he ſpeaketh of the viſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble wythdrawynge of hys bodye, he ſayeth thus: A lytle whyle, and ye ſhal not ſe me. &amp;c. It were nothynge but
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21056:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> iugglyng yf we ſhuld ſtryue, that his natural body were preſent here,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 16.</note> but inuiſiblie. For why ſhulde he, whych yet wer here, refuſe to be ſene, which ſo often tyme afters hys reſurreccion ſhewed hymſelfe to hys diſciples moſte manyfeſtly.</p>
               <p>Agayne Chriſt ſayeth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 16.</note> It is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for you that I go away. Marke that he ſayeth: that I go awaye. But yf he were here ſtyl, it were not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſarye that we ſhulde not ſe hym, but rather confortable that we myght ſe him. For he (as often as hys diſciples were amaſed and aſtonnyed at the be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>holdynge of hym) ſhewed hymſelfe playnly and openly to them. And leſt other theyr ſenſes or theyr thoughtes ſhulde ſuffer any ſuſpicion.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 24.</note> He ſayeth vnto them: Se my handes &amp; my feete: for it is euen I my ſelfe. Touche me, and handle me.</p>
               <p>And to Thomas he ſaid: put thyne hande into my ſyde.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 20.</note> And to Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lene he ſhewed hymſelfe vyſiblye.</p>
               <p>Agayne when he nowe euen go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge awaye ſhulde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mende hys diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples vnto hys father, he ſayd:</p>
               <p>Here after I wyl not be in the world. Here is vſed a Verbe ſubſtantiue,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 17.</note> as
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21056:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> well as in theſe wordes: thys is my body, that the aduerſaries maye not here ſaye, that there is a fyguratiue ſpeache, ſeyng they denye that verbes ſubſtantiues receiue any fygure. But the thynge hath no nede of theſe eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, For it foloweth in the texte: But they are in the worlde. Whyche collacion teacheth manyfeſtly, that he touchynge hys manhed is not in the world than, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hys diſciples were. And that we maye knowe whan he went awaye (not as they rather faine than expound:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 24.</note> wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he made hymſelfe inuiſible) ſo ſayeth Luke: And it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he bleſſed them, he wente awaye from them, and was caryed vp into heauen.</p>
               <p>Loo, he ſayeth not: he vanyſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye: or made hymſelfe inuiſible.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Marc.</hi> 16.</note>And Marke addeth: The Lorde af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter he had ſpoken to them was taken vp into heauen, and ſytteth on rhe ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght hande of God. He ſayeth not: He abydeth here ſtyll, but hath made his body inuiſible. In y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Actes: whyle they beheld he was take vp on hye:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 1.</note> And a cloud receyued hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of theyr ſyght. A cloud couered hym, whych had ben no nede, yf he had onely taken awaye the ſyght of him ſelfe, and otherwyſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21056:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> had ben preſent here ſtyl. Neither ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he then the takyng vp,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 1.</note> or lyftyng vp on hye. And it foloweth ther: The ſame Ieſus whyche is taken vp from you into heauen, ſhall ſo come eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ye haue ſene hym go into heauen.</p>
               <p>What is clearer than thys? he is taken away from you. Than he was not wyth them nother viſiblie nor in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiſiblie concernyng hys manhed. Wherfore, whan we ſhal ſe hym co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e agayne, lyke as he wente awaye, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall we knowe that he is preſent. Or els touchynge hys manhed, he ſytteth at the ryght hande of the father, tyll he ſhal come to iudge both the quicke and the deade.</p>
               <p>But becauſe ther is ſome that do take away place from Chriſtes body, and ſayeth that it is in no place: Let them take hede howe openly they go agaynſt the truth and ſhut theyr eyes wylfully. For they are not ignorant,<note place="margin">Chriſtes body occu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pieth a place.</note> that hys body was in the Maunger, in the Temple at Ieruſalem wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes were in theyr iorney. It was on the Croſſe, in the Graue, wythout the graue. for the Angel ſayd: he is ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, he is not here. Lo the place wher they layed hym. And that they ſhulde not ſay: that hys body is euery wher,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21056:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> let them wel marke the Aungell ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng: He is not here. And thys place: Ieſus came whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gates were ſhut and ſtode in the myddeſt of them.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 20.</note> What nede he to come, yf hys bodye be euery wher, but inuiſiblie? It had ben enough not to come, but only to ſhewe hym ſelfe, whych was bodelye there preſent before. But away wyth ſo craftely alleged tryfles, which take from vs the truthe as wel of Chriſtes manhed, as of the holy ſcriptures. Theſe aforeſayd places of ſcripture take awaye the preſence of Chriſtes body euery where, except in heauen, ſpeakyng orderly and ryght after the rule of holye ſcripture, that is, for ſo muche as we are aſſured by the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture touchynge the nature and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of the bodye taken to hym.</p>
               <p>Howe muche ſo euer contrarye places conſtrayne vs, (as whan they tell vs of the myraculous power of God) yet what ſo euer we put forth touchynge the power of God,<note place="margin">Contrary places</note> neuer ought to be wrythe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vs ſo farre that we ſhulde beleue God to do contrary vnto hys worde, for that were the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pertie of febleneſſe &amp; not of power.</p>
               <p>That wyth our mouthe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> naturall
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21056:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> body of Chriſt is not eaten, hym ſelfe ſhewed, whan he ſayde vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes ſtryuynge for the bodelye earynge of his fleſhe: The fleſhe profiteth nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6.</note> Namely to eate it naturallye, but to eate it ſpiritually profyteth much, for it gyueth lyfe.</p>
               <p>That that is borne of fleaſhe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.</note> is fleaſhe. And that that is borne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite, is ſpirite.</p>
               <p>Yf than the natural body of Chriſt be eaten wyth oure mouthe, what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynge of fleaſhe naturally eaten can be made but fleaſhe? And leſt it ſhuld be thought of any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be but an eaſy argument and a lyght reaſon let hym here, waye and conſyder the other parte. That that is borne of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite, is ſpirite.<note place="margin">The only ſpirite ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Yf than the fleaſhe of Chriſt be hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſome to the ſoule, it muſte ſpiritually and not carnally be eaten. Thys alſo pertayneth vnto the matter of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes, that the ſpirite is begotten by the ſpirite, and not by any bodelye thynge, as we ſhewed before.</p>
               <p>Paule admonyſheth,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5</note> that yf any haue knowen Chriſt at any tyme af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleaſhe, yet nowe he ſhulde not knowe hym after the fleaſhe.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:21056:39"/>
               <p>By theſe &amp; ſuche lyke places are we compelled to acknowlege, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe wordes: thys is my body muſte be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken not naturally, but figuratiuely: lyke as theſe are: Thys is the Paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. For the Lambe whych was yere by yere eaten in that great ſolempni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of holy dayes was not the natural Paſſeouer or paſſe by, but dyd ſygni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye it in times paſt to be done. To this ende alſo agreeth the ſucceſſion or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunge, becauſe the Supper co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth in the ſtede of the La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be, whych thinge putteth vs in remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt vſed lyke wordes. For the ſucceſſion kepeth the imitacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is, lyke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſpeache.</p>
               <p>The tyme alſo agreeth: for in the ſame ſupper the old paſſeouer is layd aparte and abolyſhed, and the newe thankeſgeuynge is begonne and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed.</p>
               <p>The propertie of all the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunces do agree, which chalengeth to them ſelues the name of it, wherof they make mencion and reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.<note place="margin">The Athe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nienſes.</note>
               </p>
               <p>So the people of Athens called a certayne holy daye that they had: The eaſment of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon dette, not for that the dette ſhulde yerly be diſcharged,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21056:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> but becauſe they wyth reuerence per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petually kept that that Solon had or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned in tyme paſt, and reuerenced that theyr feaſt, wyth the name of the thynge it ſelfe: So theſe thynges, that is, the bread and wyne of the ſupper, are called the body &amp; bloud of Chriſt, whych are tokens, ſygnes and reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braunces of hys very body &amp; bloude. Nowe folowe the argumentes.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶Here folowe thre argumentes.</head>
                  <p>The fyrſt. As the bodye can not be fedde wyth a ſpirituall thynge, ſo neyther y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule wyth a bodely thing. And yf the natural body of Chriſte be eaten. I aſke? whether dothe it fede the bodye or the ſoule? But it fedeth not the body, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of force it fedeth the ſoule. Yf it fede the ſoule, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſoule eateth fleaſhe, and that were not true (which is moſte true) that the ſpirite only is borne of the ſpirite.</p>
                  <p>Secondarely I aſke thys: what doth the natural body of Chriſt eaten make perfecte? Yf the forgeueneſſe of ſynnes (as one ſorte affirme) than the diſciples had forgeuenes of theyr ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes by the recept of the ſupper, and ſo
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21056:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> Chriſt dyed in vayne. Agayne, yf that that is eaten miniſtred the vertue of Chriſtes paſſion and death (as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſorte ſhewe) then the vertue of his paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion, death and redempcion was deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed before it was begonne. And yf it fede the body vnto the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion (as one certayne man very vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learnedly affirmeth) than muche mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re it ſhulde heale the body &amp; diſcharge it of ſyckneſſe.<note place="margin">Ireneus</note> But Ireneus loueth otherwyſe to be vnderſtanded, whan he wryteth: that our bodyes are nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhed vnto the reſurreccion by the bodye of Chriſt. For he ſheweth: that the hope of oure reſurreccion is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyſhed by the reſurreccion of Chriſt. Loo, thys is a pleaſaunt figuratiue ſpeache.</p>
                  <p>Thyrdlye, yf the natural bodye of Chriſte in the ſupper is gyuen to the diſciples to eate, than it foloweth of neceſſitie, that they haue eaten it as it was. But than it was paſſible (for it was not yet glorifyed) therfore they haue eaten hys paſſible bodye.<note place="margin">The obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſairies is preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>But they wyl ſaye: They dyd eate the ſame body, but not as it was paſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, but the ſame after the maner and qualities that it had after hys reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reccion.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21056:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> And we ſaye agayne: that tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other he hadde two bodyes, one that was not yet glorifyed, and the other that was glorifyed: Or els that one &amp; the ſame bodye was al at ones in the ſame tyme paſſible and impaſſible. And ſo by thys meanes foraſmuche as he ſo greatly abhorred death, Doutleſſe heretikes wold gather that he ſuffred not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paynes of death, but that he vſed thys gyft of the glorifyed body, wherby he was lackyng paine, and therfore wyll they ſaye: that he dyd not truly dye, but by diſſimulaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And thus by theſe blynd buſardes the trade of Marcions hereſie might be newly reuiued. Sex hundreth ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentes O Emperour, myght be brought, but we wyl now be content wyth theſe. But that the olde wryters are of our opinion (whych ſhalbe the laſte parte of thys article) I wyll pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue by two wytneſſes, whyche are of the chefe.</p>
                  <p>By Ambroſe whych vpon the fyrſt epiſtle to the Corinthes,<note place="margin">Ambroſe.</note> vpon theſe wordes: Shewe the Lordes death tyl he come &amp;c. ſayeth thus.</p>
                  <p>Seyng that by the death of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord we are delyuered, beynge myndfull
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21056:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> of thys thynge, in eatynge and dryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge we ſignifye the fleaſh &amp; bloud, whych are offred for vs. &amp;c. Ambroſe ſpeaketh of the meate and drynke of the ſupper, &amp; ſheweth, that we ſignifie theſe very thynges, whyche were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred for vs.</p>
                  <p>By Awſten alſo, whych in the thyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie treatie vpon Iohns Goſpel affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth:<note place="margin">Awſten in the <hi>30</hi> trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie vpon Iohns Goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell..</note> that Chriſtes bodye that roſe from the dead muſt by but in one pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce. Wher the printed exemplares ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue (may) for (muſt) but coruptlye. For both in the Maſter of ſentence and in the Decrees (wherinto this ſentence of Awſten is tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated) it is red muſt. Wherby we maye openly ſee, that what ſo euer the olde writters ſpake honorably of the ſupper, they dyd vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly vnderſtand it, not of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral eatyng of the body of Chriſt, but of the ſpirituall.</p>
                  <p>The ſame Awſten agaynſt <hi>Adiman<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tus.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Awſten a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimantus, <hi>.12.</hi> chap.</note> 12 chap. teacheth: that theſe thre ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tences: the bloud is the ſowle: thys is my body: and, the ſtone was Chriſt: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſpoken ſacramentally, that is, as he ſpeaketh in a ſigne, and figurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely. And amonge many other thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges at lengthe he commeth to theſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21056:41"/> wordes: I maye alſo interprete thys commaundemente to be put in a ſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. For the Lord dowted not to ſaye: Thys is my body, whan he gaue a ſyg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of hys body. Thus ſayth Awſten.</p>
                  <p>Loo,<note place="margin">A keye.</note> here we haue a keye wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we maye open all the ſaynges of the olde wrytters towchyng thys article of the ſupper: that that whych only is the ſigne of the body, he ſayth is called the body.</p>
                  <p>Let them go nowe that wyll, and condempne vs of hereſye, ſo that they knowe therby alſo them ſelues agaynſt the Decrees of Byſſhoppes to condempne the chefe pyllare and ſtaye of diuines.</p>
                  <p>Of theſe thinges it is made moſt manifeſt,<note place="margin">The olde writters ſpake ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tally, whan they reaſoned of the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of eati<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Chriſtes body.</note> that the olde wrytters al waye ſpake ſacramentally, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they gaue ſo much to the eatinge of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes body in the ſupper, namly, that the ſacramentall eatinge of Chriſtes body could not clenſe the ſowle, but fayth in God through Ieſus Chriſte, which is the ſpirituall eatinge, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of this outwarde eatinge, is a token and ſhadowe. For lyke as bread ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth the body, and wyne comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, nurryſſheth, quyckeneth, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſheth,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21056:42"/> and maketh a man mery: Euen ſo it ſtrengthneth and ſuſtey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth the ſycke ſoule, and aſſureth it of the mercy of God, becauſe he hath ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to vs his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne: &amp; ſo lykewyſe it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſſheth, and maketh mery y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynd, that our ſinnes (wherwith it was vex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed) are quenched in his bleſſed bloud.</p>
                  <p>At thys tyme we wyl holde vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent wyth theſe, albeit one myght ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke hole bokes to declare &amp; proue that the olde wryters are of oure opinion in thys matter. Neyther let the lytle boke of Eccius latly put forth touchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the opinion of the olde wrytters diſco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rage any man, for ſhortly, by the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of God, we ſhall ſe the confutacion of it, by the great learned ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther Ecolampadius, whoſe laboure hath bene fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begynnyng of thys controuerſye to enſerche and gather out the myndes of the olde wryters touchynge the ſame. But in thys mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter theſe thynges that maye be requy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red for the more fuller declaracion herof, or confutacion of our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, we whyche are of thys opinion haue (as I thynke) abundantly perfourmed by many bokes written vnto dyuers men.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="article">
               <head>¶The .ix. Article.</head>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:21056:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Nynth. I beleue that the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies,<note place="margin">Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies.</note> whych by ſuperſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are nother contrarie to fayth, nor to the word of God, (albeit I knowe not whether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuche maye be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de) may thrughe charitie be ſuffred, til y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyght of know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege more and more ſhyne vpon vs. But I beleue alſo (the ſame charitie beynge maſtres) that the ſayd ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies (whan wythout great offence it maye be done) are to be abolyſhed, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the vnfaythful crye out neuer ſo muche agaynſt it.<note place="margin">Images owght to be atken awaye yf ther be any peryll of worſhippi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge them.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But I thynke that ymages, which are ſet vp to be worſhipped are not to be accompted amonge ceremonies, but are of the nombre of thoſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whyche are vtterly contrarye to Goddes word. But thoſe that are not ſet vp to be worſhipped, or wher ther is no daunger of worſhippyng them here after, it is ſo farre of that I wyll condemne them, that I acknowlege both the paynters and caruers crafte to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gyftes of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="article">
               <head>¶The .x. Article.</head>
               <p>Tenth. I beleue that the office of prophecie and of preachynge God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des worde is an holy thyng, and that amonge al offices it is moſte neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21056:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> For to ſpeake directly after the ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le of ſcripture, we ſe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge al people that the outwarde preachynge of the Apoſtles, Euangeliſtes, Byſhoppes &amp; Paſtours went before fayth, whyche fayth neuertheleſſe we attribute vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſpirite only. For (alaſſe) we ſe very many which heare the outward preaching of the Goſpel, but they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue not, which happeneth for lack of the ſpirite. Whither ſo euer therfore Prophetes or Preachers of Goddes word are ſent, it is a ſingler token of Goddes fauore, that he wyl vnto hys electe open the knowledge of hym ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe. And contrary wyſe, to whom true preachers are denyed, it is a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that Goddes wrath hangeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them. As we maye gather of the Prophetes and of the example of S. Paule, whyche ſomtyme was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bydde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to go to certein, and ſometyme called vnto other. And truth it is, that both the lawes them ſelues &amp; the Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſtrates can by nothynge more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently be furthered toward the defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of publike iuſtice, than by the ſincere preachynge of Goddes worde. For in vayne is ryght and equitie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, excepte it be to them, that both re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>garde
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21056:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> it and loue it. And thervnto the preachers as miniſters prepare the mindes, but the ſpirite is the worker, as author both of the preacher and of the hearer. We alſo acknowlege that kynde of miniſters, namely, whyche teacheth, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forteth, affrayeth, careth for, and faythfully loketh to the ſaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of the people of Chriſt. And alſo that, that baptiſeth, that in the holy ſupper miniſtreth the body &amp; bloude of the Lorde (for ſo we alſo figuratiue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye cal the holy bread and wyne of the ſupper.) And further we acknowlege that ſorte of miniſters, that viſiteth the ſycke: that miniſtreth to the poore wyth the almes and in the name of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</p>
               <p>And finally y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, that in ſcholes teacheth, openly readeth and interpreteth, that other themſelues or other may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed that hereafter they maye ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue rule of congregacions.</p>
               <p>But that monſtrouſe mitred and croſyard kynd of Papiſticall byſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes we beleue to be lordly loyterers, baſtardes and vnlawful chyldren. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is a no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre borne to conſume vytayles, an vnprofytable burthen of the earthe, and fynally to be vtterlye
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21056:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> that thyng in the body of the church, that byles, botches, we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes and impo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtumes are in mannes body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="article">
               <head>¶The .xi. Article.</head>
               <p>ELeuenth. I knowe that the Magiſtrate ryghtly choſen &amp; admitted is Goddes lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt aſwel as the preacher. For as the preacher is the mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſter of the heauenly wyſedome and goodnes, as he that faythfullye tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth and rebuketh ſinne and errour: ſo the Magiſtrate is the miniſter of goodnes and ryghteouſnes. Of good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, that wyth faythfulnes and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perancie lyke vnto God he may both heare and ſe vnto the cauſes, matters and buſyneſſes of his people. Of righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſnes, that he may repreſſe, holde downe, breake and punyſhe the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the wycked: and ſupport main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne and defende the innocentes. Yf a Prince haue theſe gyftes, I bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue that hys ſubiectes nede not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayed of his conſcience. Yf he lacke them, and yet for al that wyll ſhewe hymſelfe terrible and to be feared, I beleue that his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce by no meanes
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21056:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be diſcharged therfor, becauſe he is ryghtly choſen and admytted. But yet alſo I beleue that a chriſten man ought to obey ſuche a tyraunt, vnto ſuche an occaſion as Paule ſpeaketh of: Yf thou mayſt be fre, rather vſe it. Whyche occaſion neuertheleſſe I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue to be ſhewed of God onely,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> &amp; not of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that not obſcurely, but as openly as Saule was abiecte, and Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid taken to be his ſucceſſour. And as touchynge payeng of tribute and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome for our defece, I vtterly thinke as Paule doth. Rom. 13.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="article">
               <head>¶The .xii. Artitle.</head>
               <p>Twelfte. I beleue that that forged fable of the fyre of Purgatorie is as blaſphemouſe a thynge agaynſt the free rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pcion purchaſed by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes bloude, as it hath ben gaynful to the authors, inuentours and mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayners therof. For yf it be neceſſary wyth paynes and torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes to waſhe away the deſeruinges of our ſynnes, than ſhal Chriſte be deade in vayne, and than is grace of none effecte. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whych thyng, what can be thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght more wicked in the chriſten com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mone
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21056:45" rendition="simple:additions"/> welthe, ſtate and condicion? Or what maner of Chriſt haue they, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che wyl themſelues to be called chriſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>anes, and yet are afrayed of this fyre, naye, no fyre nowe, but a ſmoke?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Holl.</note>But as towchinge hell, wher with <hi>Ixion</hi> &amp; <hi>Tantalus</hi> the vnfaythfull, diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient and ſtubburne enemyes of God are euerlaſtingly punyſſhed, I do not only beleue that it is, but I ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rely knowe it. For when the truthe it ſelfe ſpeaketh of the vniuerſall iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te, he ſheweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> after that iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t certayn ſhal go into euerlaſtyng fyre.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5.</note> Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vniuerſal iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ther ſhalbe an euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g fyre. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Anabaptiſtes ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not colorably cloke their erroure, wherby they teache,</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſtes erroure is confuted.</note>That <hi>Euerlaſtinge</hi> ſhall not conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue after the generall iudgemente. For here Chriſte ſpeaketh of an euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge fyre after the iudgemente, whych ſhal burne and tormente the deuell with his aungels, with the wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked that deſpiſe God, with the Tyrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes which with lyes oppreſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth, and with the vnmercifull, whyche of tender compaſſyon and fayth releue not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> neceſſytie of theyr neyghbour. Theſe aforſayd artycles I ſtedfaſtlye
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21056:45"/> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue, teache &amp; defende, not with myne owne wordes, but wyth the notable ſentences of Goddes holy worde.</p>
               <p>And I promyſe and profeſſe (God ſo wyllyng) to do the ſame ſo longe as I lyue. Excepte any man by the decrees of the very holye ſcriptures ryghtlye vnderſtanded can as plainly and ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly (as we haue done theſe) declare, pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue and confirme the contrarie. Vnto vs doutleſſe it is no leſſe pleaſaunt &amp; acceptable than ryght and lawful to ſubmitte our wrytynges and aſſerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the holy ſcriptures, and to the Churche by the ſpirite iudginge the ſame. We myght haue declared all theſe articles more plenteouſlye and at length, but ſeynge the tyme wolde not ſuffer vs, we ar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent with theſe. Whiche we thynke to be ſuche, as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maye eaſely pynche at (for ſo is the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now a dayes) but no man ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble worthelye to confute and auoyde them. Neuertheles yf any wyl aſſaye he ſhall (by Goddes grace) not eſcape vnanſwered. For than perchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce we ſhall brynge forth the reſydue of oure artillarie and ordenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, wherof we haue good ſtore and plentye behynde but theſe are ſufficient for this tyme.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:21056:46"/>
               <p>Wherfore moſte prudent Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and ye other princes, lordes of great power, and nobles of hyghe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and fynally ye learned Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadoures and heades of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, I praye and beſeche you all, for Chriſte Ieſus ſake the Lorde and our brother: for his mercy and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſake: for his iudgement ſake: (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whyche, wil ye nyl ye you muſte al come and gyue a rekening of your procedynges) wherin he ſhall rendre vnto euery one accordyng to theyr de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſertes: from whome no cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel is hyd: whyche by the Prophete threatneth woo to them that ſaye,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 10.5.</note> good is euell and euell good: and to the makers of wycked lawes: whych ſubuerteth and ouerthroweth the deuiſes and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of princes wickedly deliberating and vngodly decreyng,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.</note> enacting, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncyng, eſtablyſhyng and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge any thynge agaynſt Goddes wyll, yea (I ſaye once againe) I moſt humbly deſyre you all for hys cauſe, that aduaunceth the humble and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth downe the proude, deſpyſe not the ſympleneſſe and baceneſſe of me admonyſhynge you ſo wyſe and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men in the begynnynge. For foo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:21056:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> Idiotes and ſymple men haue of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten ſpoken many thynges in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note> And the truth it ſelfe hath choſen to be publyſhed and preached of men of rude, ſymple and lowe eſtate.</p>
               <p>Agayne, remembre that ye your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues are men alſo, whyche both maye diſceaue and be diſceaued.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.</note> For euery man is a lyer, and vnleſſe he be other<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe taught by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſpiracion of God, than he hym ſelfe other knoweth or deſireth, ther is nothynge to be loked for of hym, but by hys owne crafte &amp; counſel to hurle downe hym ſelfe.</p>
               <p>For ful truly ſayd Ieremye the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete: Loo, they haue refuſed the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des worde, what wyſedome than can remayne in them ſelfus? Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, foraſmuche as youre ſelues are the prelates and ryngleaders of rygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, no men oughte ſo muche as you to haue the ſure and certayne knowledge of the wyl of God. which, from whence can it be fetched and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyred, than out of hys holy ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res? Abhorre not therfore theyr myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des which lean holly to goddes word. For co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly we ſe it happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that the more the aduerſaries ſtryue agaynſt it, ſo muche the more a great deale
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21056:47"/> it floryſheth and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to lyght, and errour and falſhed is caſt oute of the dores. But yf amonge you ther be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (as I knowe ther is) that wyl ſtout<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye deminiſhe and diffame oure lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge vnto you, and wyll ſaye: that we are ygnoraunt and lacke know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, yea and that we are maliciouſe alſo, yet thinke this with your ſelues: Fyrſt, whether we whych folow this maner of preachynge the goſpel, and the ryght vſe of miniſtracion of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crament of thankes gyuyng, haue at any tyme ſo ordered our lyues, that a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny good man hathe douted, whether we ought to be reputed and taken as good, honeſt and faythfull men? And agayne, whether euen from our cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels we haue ben ſo eſtraunged from wytte and erudicion, that all hope of learnynge ſhulde vtterlye be caſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye from vs? vndoutedly we glorie of nother of theſe, ſeynge that Paule hymſelfe ſayeth: that what ſo euer he was, it was al of the gyft of God. Neuertheleſſe, yf our lyfe haue hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened ſometyme (by the benefyte of God) to be ſomewhat proſperous and pleaſaunt, yet wholly was it neuer gi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen to riote, exceſſe and fylthynes at
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:21056:47"/> any tyme, neither yet (God be praiſed therfore) hath degenerated into cruel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, pryde, and obſtinacie, ſo that the wytnes of our lyfe (through Goddes benefite) hath many tymes ſtayed the deuiſes of our aduerſaries, and made them ſo aſtonyed, that they haue rety<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red backe againe. And as for our lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge, albeit it is greater then oure aduerſaries other can beare, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, or without conſcience deſpiſe, yet is it farre leſſe than they that ten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derly loue vs, iudge it to be. But yet to comme to oure purpoſe, we haue ſo not a fewe yeres bene ſowldiars &amp; ſtudentes both in holy ſcripture and in mannes learnynge, that there is no cauſe why y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhuld nowe teache any thynge raſſhly. We maye law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully prayſe the grace and free gyftes of God ſo lyberaly diſtributed to our congregations. For owt of al dowte ſo haue oure congregacions (whyche here the Lord God by our miniſterie) receaued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of truth,<note place="margin">The frutes of the true doctrine of Goddes words.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyeng &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>truth are ſhroncken: pryde, ryote and exceſſe are broken: reuilynge, ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge, chydynge and diſſencion are trudged awaye from amonge vs, whyche doutleſſe, yf they be not the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21056:48" rendition="simple:additions"/> frutes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſpirite, what are they els? Conſyder wyth your ſelues, O moſte myghtye Emperoure and all ye princes &amp; nobles,<note place="margin">The frutes of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes traditions</note> what good frute thys vyſar of mannes doctrine hathe brought to you. The Maſſes that are bought and ſolde, as they haue increa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed the outragious luſte and wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe as well of princes as of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſo haue they brought in and enlar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged the fylthy luſte &amp; exceſſiue pryde of Popes, cardinalles, and byſhoppes and the vnſaciable couetouſnes and gluttony of mercyleſſe Maſſemo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers What myſcheue is it, that thys maſſe marte, with choppinge, chaunginge, byinge and ſellinge therof hath not procured and ſet forwarde? who is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to waſt and ſcatter abrode the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedyng rycheſſe that is heaped toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by maſſynge, except they be ſtop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped and ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gled euen in the vaynes &amp; that in tyme? God therfore muche better refourme theſe thynges than you all, whome we gladly bothe cal &amp; beleue to be the chefe and moſt mygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye here in earth, &amp; graunt you grace to cut awaye the rootes of that wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Maſſe and of al other errours in the churche, and that you may bring
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21056:48"/> o paſſe, that Proude Rome wyth all her dirtie dregges, whyche ſhe hathe thruſted into al chriſtendome, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially into your Germany, may be vt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terly forſaken and lefte. And as you tender your owne ſaluacions, what power ſo euer you haue hytherto exe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuted agaynſt the puritie of Chriſtes Goſpell, that you maye haue grace nowe at the laſte wholly to bende the ſame agaynſt the wycked inforceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the vngodly Papiſtes, that true ryghteouſneſſe whych thorowe your negligences is banyſhed, and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, whych is obſcured with fained and counterfeated coloures, maye be brought agayne vnto vs.</p>
               <p>Ther is enough and to muche cru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eltie executed already, except without a cauſe and contrary to ryght to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde, to condempne, to torment, yea to ſpoyle, bannyſhe, and kyl be not tyrannouſe or cruell.</p>
               <p>Therfore, ſeyng it goeth not wel for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward wyth youre thys waye, you muſt ſurely go an other waye to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke. Yf this counſel be of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 5.</note> ſtryue not agaynſt God. If it be any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe, it wyl dowtleſſe fal in the own folyſſhneſſe. Wherfore O ſonnes of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21056:49"/> men who ſo euer ye be, ſuffer the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of God freely to be ſpred abrode &amp; to ſpring furth. Remember y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it lyeth not in your power (if God wyl haue it growe) to forbydde and let the graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it growe not. Ye ſee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> this frut of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel is abo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly watered with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauenly ſhowers, neyther with any heate of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it be i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forced to wyther and fade awaye. Conſyder not what ye moſt deſyre, but what in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Goſpel the worlde requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. what ſo euer thys is, take it in good worth, &amp; by your counſels, deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and determinacyons, ſhewe your ſelues to be the chyldren of God.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>At Zuryk <date>the 3. daye of Iuly, in the yere of our Lord. 1530.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Vnto your noble Maieſtie and vnto al faythful men, your moſt obedient ſubiecte Huldryk Zwinglius by the grace, callyng and ſendyng of God, flockfeeder of the congregacion of Zuryk.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:21056:49"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The copy of an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle wrytten from Copyn hauen</hi>
               </hi> in Denmarke vnto an Englyſhe Marchaunt dwellyng at Wyncheſtre in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</head>
            <p>THe grace and peace of God be gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto you through Ieſus Chriſt. &amp;c. Where as in your laſte letters to me moſte truſtye and aſſured frende you inſtantlye deſyred me to wryte vnto you, what I haue redde &amp; marked in holy ſcripture touchynge the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion of ſynnes. Truly ſyr this your reaſonable requeſt I wolde, yf I were able ryght gladly ſatiſfye. But as you knowe I am yet but a yong lynge, and as one ſhulde ſay but a nouyce in the ſtudye of diuinitie, &amp; farre vnable to penne thys matter ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cordynge to the worthyneſſe therof. Neuertheleſſe wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I conſyder wyth my ſelfe, howe muche I am bounden to you, partly for your louynge kynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe dayly ſhewed to my poore kynſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke and frendes in Wincheſter, and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21056:50"/> partly for your lyberal gyftes &amp; chari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table exhibicion that I receiued from you whan I was ſtudent at Oxforde, I can not but thynke it to be my bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den dutie ſomwhat to gratifye you a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gayne. And albeit that ignoraunce, rudeneſſe of ſtyle &amp; lacke of learnyng plucketh me backe from the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dlyng of thys matter, yet the conſyderacion of your great diſcrecion and gentyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes prycketh me forwarde to atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte what I can do therin. Certeſſe I no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doure, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you wyl ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte my ſymple rudeneſſe, goodwyll and endeuoure in this behalf, no leſſe then yf the matter were gloriouſlye garnyſhed with eloquence &amp; ſet forth wyth the moſte probable perſuaſions of the freſheſt Philoſopher or rethori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion in Oxforde. I truſte you wyl cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite and embrace the truth though it be neuer ſo bacely and homly wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or declared vnto you. For the truthe ſhal abyde and floryſhe, whan al pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane paynted perſuaſions and fond Phariſaical phantaſies ſhal vanyſh a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>waye and be ſcattered abrode as drye duſte before a whyrle wynde. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for to kepe you no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thys mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, I ſhal be Goddes grace, ſo ſhortly
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21056:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> as I can declare vnto you, what I haue learned &amp; marked in holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture concernyng thys article of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of ſynnes. And that is thys that foloweth.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Of Confeſſion of ſynnes.</head>
               <p>THe holy Scripture doth dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly in ſundrye places ſet forth and treate of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of ſynnes.<note place="margin">A general confeſſyon.</note> In ſome places it maketh mencion of a general and ſolempne confeſſion openly made of all the people beyng aſſembled and gathered to gither at thappointemente, callyng and exhor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacion of their hygh Magiſtrate, Byſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhoppe, curate or publyke miniſter of Goddes worde. The cauſe therof was commonly ſomme great plage, vengeaunce or punyſſhement wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God ſcourged them for their ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful, heynouſe and abhominable of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences committed and done by them and theyr for fathers. example therof we haue in the ſecond boke of Eſdras wher it is thus writtyn:</p>
               <p>In the foure and twentie daye of thys monech came the chyldren of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rael<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Neem.</hi> 9.</note>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:21056:51"/> to gether, with faſtinge and ſack clothes and earth vpon them, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated the ſede of Iſrael from al the ſtraunge chyldren, and ſtode &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leged theyr ſynnes and the wycked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of theyr fathers, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſtode vp in theyr place and redde in the boke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord theyr God four tymes on the daye. &amp;c. And after a ſolempne reherſal of the iudgementes &amp; greate mercyfulneſſe of God declared in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcripture, they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude thus, ſayeng: Thou (O God) arte ryghteous in all that thou haſte broughte vpon vs, for thou haſte done ryght. As for vs, we haue bene vngodly, and our kynges, princes, preſtes and fathers haue not done after thy lawe, nor regarded thy commaundementes and thyne ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt exhortacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wherwyth thou haſt exhorted them, and haue not ſerued the in thy kyngdome &amp; in thy great goodes that thou gaueſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c. and are not conuerted from theyr wycked workes. Beholde therfore are we in bondage thys daye. Yea euen in the lande that thou gaueſt vnto oure fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to enioy the frutes and goodes therof, behold ther are we bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Lo, here is a ſolempne open confeſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:21056:51"/> Wolde God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thys exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blyke confeſſion of ſynnes were well practiſed through out all chriſtendo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, namely at thys daye, ſeynge that the plages of God do dayly increaſe more and more vpon vs, our ſynful lyues &amp; abhominacions iuſtlye deſeruynge the ſame and muche more.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Thre mo ſortes of confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſynnes.</head>
               <p>Ther are alſo thre mo ſortes of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of ſynnes declared in the holy ſcriptures. The fyrſt is ſecrete confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſynne only vnto God.</p>
               <p>The ſeconde is an open confeſſion before men.</p>
               <p>The thyrde is a priuate &amp; ſecrete confeſſion made vnto man.</p>
               <p>As touchynge the fyrſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Confeſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto God only.</note> it is an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble and lowlye confeſſion of ſynnes made vnto God euen from the verye herte. As whan a ſynner examyneth hys lyfe by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes of God, &amp; ſo fyndeth hys conſcience bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened and accombred wyth ſynne, &amp; feeleth therby what daunger of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion that he is in: thys feelynge of hys ſycke conſcience wyl greatly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:21056:52" rendition="simple:additions"/> hym to ſeke a phiſicyon. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he perceaueth that ther is no medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyn wyll heale hys dyſeaſe but only the mercy of God, he wyl not ceaſſe to make all the ſute that he can to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne it. He wyl withowt any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>laye proſtrate hym ſelfe before God, and with an humble, lowly and contrite herte and mynd acknowledge him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe greuouſly to haue offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maieſtie in thought, conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacyon, worde and ded<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> leaue of hys lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table ſute and fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful prayer &amp; requeſte of this his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful mercy, tyl he obteyn it. The ſwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>linge rage of hys putrifyed conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce wyl neuer be aſſwaged, tyl the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyouſe oyle of Goddes mercy haue ſuppled it, mitigated it, quieted it, and vtterly cured and healed it. Of thys maner of confeſſyon the holy ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re doth many tymes treate, doth by playne authoritie and examples <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> authoritie.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Authoritie.</hi> 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.</note> If we knowledge our ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes (ſayth S. Iohn) God is faythfull and iuſte to forgeue vs owr ſynnes, and to clenſe vs from all vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Example.</note>Examples ther be many. Of whyche I wyl at thys tyme contente
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:21056:52" rendition="simple:additions"/> my ſelfe with two or thre. Kyng Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid felynge the intollerable burthen of his ſynnes, cryed out, ſayeng:<note place="margin">Dauid.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Haue mercy vpon me (O God) after thy great goodnes.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.</note> And according vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to thy great mercies, do awaye myne offences. Waſhe me againe from my wyckednes, &amp; clenſe me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſinne. For I knowlege my fautes, and my ſynne is euer before me.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.</note> Agaynſt the only, agaynſt the haue I ſynned, for thy names ſake (O Lorde) be merciful vnto my ſynne, for it is great.<note place="margin">The pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blicane. Luc. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>The Publicane alſo ſayeth: be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful (O God) to me a ſynner.</p>
               <p>This confeſſion and knowleging of our ſynnes vnto God yf with a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trite and ſorowful herte it be done in fayth, God (which knoweth the ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of euery mans mynde) wil accept &amp; allowe though the repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſynner vttereth not one worde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his mouth</p>
               <p>Exemple of the ſynful woman,<note place="margin">The ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Luc. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> that came vnto Chriſt. She ſpake no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge, but wepte, and lowlye fell downe at Chriſtes feete, and waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the teares of her eyes, and dryed them wyth the heeres of her head, and annoynted them wyth oyntmente.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:21056:53"/>
               <p>All whyche thynges were euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of her true and vnfayned repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of her ſynnes and frutes of her ſure faythe that ſhe had in Chriſtes goodnes. For whoſe comforte Chriſte ſayde: thy ſynnes are forgeuen thee. thy fayth hath ſaued thee: go thy way in peace. This earneſte confeſſion of ſynnes vnto god ſhuld euery chriſtian dayly practyſe &amp; exercyſe vnfaynedly.</p>
               <p>Of thys aforeſayd confeſſyon to God ſpryngeth out the confeſſyon of our own ſynfulneſſe before men.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2</hi> Confeſſyon of ſymnes befor men.</note> For he that hath felt a taſt af the mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy of God as he ſhal ſe occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to glori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fie God by hys exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple wil not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med other priuatly before one man, or openly before many men, yea though al the whole world were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente, to confeſſe him ſelf to haue bene an horrible tranſgreſſoure of Goddes holy commaundementes. He wyll nothyng dowte, but that he with this hys meke confeſſyon ſhal moch glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God, and moue the hearers by hys example to abhorre ſynne and chaunge their euel lyfe. Of thys we haue an euident example in God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des choſen veſſel S. Paule, whyche af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter hys conuerſyon vnto the fayth of Chriſte was not aſhamed many ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act</hi> 22.26</note>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:21056:53" rendition="simple:additions"/> openlye to confeſſe before men, what an vnmercyful tyraunt and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gracious grafte he was agaynſt the holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacion of Chriſt, before his conuerſion to the fayth. Thys thinge alſo aſhamed he not to wryte and ſet forth to the hole world, ſayeng: I am not worthy to be called an Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 1. <hi>Timo.</hi> 1.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe I perſecuted the congregacion of God. And in an other place he ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: I was a blaſphemer, and a perſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuter, and a tyraunt. &amp;c. And after: Chriſte Ieſus came into the worlde to ſaue ſynners, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I am chefe.</p>
               <p>Thys example of S. Paule very fewe of the Papiſtes in Englande ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue followed,<note place="margin">Fewe of the papiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed this example.</note> vnleſſe it were by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint for feare of bodely punyſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t And therfore for my parte I ſuſpecte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to remayne Papiſtes ſtyl in their hertes. For yf they had vnfaynedlye abhorred papiſtrie, they wolde after thys exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of S. Paule wyth al theyr hertes haue confeſſed them ſelues to haue bene diſceyued, and alſo to haue wyth falſe doctrine diſceyued the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, and therfore haue openly and her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tely aſked them mercye for the ſame: by doyng wherof doutleſſe they ſhuld very muche haue glorifyed God.</p>
               <p>The thyrde maner of confeſſion<note place="margin" type="runSum">3</note>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:21056:54"/> of ſynnes is a priuate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is of two ſortes. The firſt is for the direccion, eſtablyſhment &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience towardes God. The other is touchynge the reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciliation &amp; confeſſion of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes faut &amp; treſpace to his neighbour whom he hath offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded.<note place="margin">Priuate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſyon of ſynne is nedfull to many for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowlege, counſell &amp; conforte.</note> And as touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt waye of priuate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion vnto man, I thynke it is a good &amp; holſome ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner &amp; facion conuenient &amp; nedeful to be vſed &amp; obſerued of many of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des people for thre cauſes, that is, for knowlege, counſel and for comforte.</p>
               <p>Fyrſt for knowlege: As wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple man or woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hath herd lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le or no preachynge of Goddes word,<note place="margin">For know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge.</note> by reaſon wherof they haue almoſte no knowlege of God or hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementes, neither of the profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of baptime, neither of fayth, neither ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue they in a maner any knowlege at al of the waye of ſaluacion by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes death. Is it not nedeful (thinke you) for ſuch ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ꝑſones to hunt &amp; ſeke out ſome diſcrete &amp; learned mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of goddes word, &amp; to knowlege vnto hym theyr great ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; to requyre at hys mouth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowlege of the lawe of the Lorde &amp; of the waye of ſaluacion?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Malac.</hi> 2.</note> Is it not wrytten, that the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:21056:54" rendition="simple:additions"/> preſtes lyppes ſhuld be ſure of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, that men maye ſeke the lawe at hys mouthe, for he is a meſſenger of the Lorde of hooſtes? It is mete ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſtes ſhulde haue good know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege in goddes holy worde, for they ar appointed to be ſhepeherdes ouer the flocke of Chriſte, to fede the ſoules of goddes people with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> delicate fode of goddes word, &amp; ſpecially with that ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly breade of lyfe Chriſte Ieſu, that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e downe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſaue al his people fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſynnes. But alaſſe for pitie, the ſpirituall ſhepherdes into many places of the worlde &amp; ſpecially in En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gland are very rude, vnlearned &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>able to teache other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues lacke the knowlege &amp; ryght vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng of the holy ſcriptures. For howe ſhulde they teach other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge vnlearned their ſelues? Dout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it hath bene herd of in not a few places of England,<note place="margin">It is very ſtraunge that the ſhepe ſhuld haue more witte &amp; learninge than the ſhepperd.</note> that the pariſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner hath be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> better lerned in holy ſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pture than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parſon or vicare, whych thing is muche to be lamented. Is it not a great ſhame, yea is it not vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt nature; that the ſhepe ſhuld be wyſer and better learned than the ſhepeherde. But no men are ſo much in this bebalfe to be blamed, as
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:21056:55"/> the Babilonical byſhoppes, partly for admittyng ſuche doltyſh dodipoles to the office of preſthed: and partlye for the inſtitutynge to fat benefyces and to the cure and charge of chriſten ſou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les ſo many vnlearned idiotes, which nother ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor wyl fede them with the ſpiritual foode of Goddes word. Our Lorde redreſſe thys matter. Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">For cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel</note>Secondarely, thys priuate confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is very nedfull for counſel, ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly for ſuche perſones, whoſe conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are accumbred wyth ſcrupulouſe ſuperſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of meates, vowes, or with perpleexd doutes in cauſes of matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monye, of reſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of wronge gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or wytholden goodes, of reconciliaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſuche other: Or els, yf they be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore aſſaulted wyth dyuers temptaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of theyr goſtly enemye the deuel, &amp; know no remedies how to auoyde them. In al theſe and ſuche lyke dout<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful caſes, whome oughte they rather to go vnto and aſke counſell, then of the heardman of theyr ſoules? In worldly affayres &amp; buſyneſſes which waye a man maye defende his ryght tytle of enheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; how he may o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe his aduerſarye that wolde do hym wronge, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyl ſpare for no
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:21056:55" rendition="simple:additions"/> laboure nor coſt, but wyll retayne of theyr cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt learned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of lawe that they can get: Muche more in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritual matters for the ſoules healthe ought euery true chriſtian to ſeke for the beſt learned &amp; diſcreteſt miniſters of goddes worde, to ſatiſfye their con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſciences in doutful cauſes, &amp; to ſhewe them apt remedies for the auoidinge of their ſundrie temptacions of their goſtly enemie the deuel. For yf he be a good ſpiritual phiſicion, he wyl mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter vnto the patient a conuenient medicine for the healyng of his ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſyckneſſe &amp; diſeaſe. And the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes dutie (yf he wyll recouer hys health) is no leſſe than tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfully &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bediently to embrace and receyue the wholſome cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel of his ſpiritual phiſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion. For the wyſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayeth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 12. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.</note> He that is wyſe wyl be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelled. Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iohn the Baptiſt preached in the diſert, the people came vnto hym fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; al the regions rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d about Iordan, &amp; were baptiſed of hym in Iordan, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſing their ſynnes. And the puplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes cam alſo to be baptiſed,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 3.</note> &amp; ſayd vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to him: Maſter, what ſhal we do? Loo here the publicanes, which were very extorcioners &amp; brybers, ar y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preachi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:21056:56"/> of Iohn the baptiſt came vnto repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, &amp; callyng hym maiſter aſked him counſel howe they ſhulde order their lyues. Than he lyke a diſcrete goſtly father ſaid vnto them thus: Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quire no more than is appointed you As though he ſhulde ſay: for as much as heretofore you haue ben extorcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners &amp; very caterpillers &amp; brybers, &amp; haue taken more of the poore people for taſke, tribute &amp; cuſtome then you ought to haue done: Nowe ſeyng you are conuerted &amp; become the diſciples of the heauenly doctrine, you muſte wyth all diligence chaunge your euel life into a better, &amp; oppreſſe the people no le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, but take your appointed du<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties &amp; no more. So lykewyſe the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers alſo aſked hym &amp; ſayd: what ſhal we do than? And he ſayd vnto them: Do no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> violence nor wronge, &amp; be content with your wages, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Yf the ſame trade were lykewyſe had in vſe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge vs that are now ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, ſo that whan ſo euer we were encombred wyth any greuouſe te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion, or entangled or ouerthrowen in the ſame, yf we euen than aſſone as we could poſſible wolde conſult with our ſoules phiſicion, to knowe which
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:21056:56"/> waye we myght beſt auoyde the tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptacion hereafter, were it not a godly faſſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; worthy prayſe &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</p>
               <p>Exemple:<note place="margin">An exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> Yf a yonge man beynge ſore tempted vnto whordome, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times ouercome of his temptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hath yelden &amp; gyuen hym ſelfe ouer vnto the deuell for that tyme, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge the very acte of fylthy whordo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e &amp; adultery: Yf he (I ſaye) vpon the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſideracion of hys owne da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable ſtare that he ſtandeth in, wolde go vnto a diſcrete, godly &amp; wel learned preacher of Goddes worde, &amp; playnly vtter vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him his abhominable dedes in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral wordes, &amp; aſke hys beſt counſel &amp; aduyſe therin. Truly this preacher wolde fyrſt declare vnto hym by god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des worde, what great dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of eter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nal damnacion that he than ſtode in, &amp; playnly tel hym that God ſayeth in the holy ſcripture: that nother whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers nor adulterers ſhal enherit the kyngdome of God: And that God threatneth to iudge &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempne both adulterers and fornicatours. And ſo groundynge himſelfe vpon theſe ſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptures and ſuch lyke, therby beating into hys conſcience the feare of God, he wolde bydde hym in any wyſe ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtlye
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:21056:57"/> repente himſelfe of hys great ſynne, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitte hym ſelfe by ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, faythfull and continuall prayer to the mercye of God in Chriſt Ieſu. And in any wyſe without any delaye refuſe that fylthy and deteſtable faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyon of lyuynge, or els, though he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med neuer ſo moche outwardly in thys myſerable worlde to floryſhe, yet ſhuld he continually lyue without the fauoure of God, and vnder hys greate wrath and vengeance, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge in that ſtate the ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, but the deuels ſlaue and bondman, owe of Goddes kyngdom, and ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te to eternall death and damnacyon.</p>
               <p>Thys thynge earneſtly herd, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently weyed, and deply from the y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very herte conſydered: If thys ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner were one of Goddes flocke,<note place="margin">Howe a great ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhuld v<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe him ſelfe to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of God.</note> at the hearinge of thys terryble ſentence of the lawe, he wold tremble and quake for feare, wepe, wayle and lament his horrible and deteſtable ſtate, crye and call inceſſauntly for the vnſpeakable mercy of God in Chriſte Ieſu, truſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge by hys only meanes to obteyn and get agayn the fauour of God, whych thorowe hys careleſſe diſobedience he he had loſt. And further he wold hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:21056:57"/> deſyre counſell, whyche waye he myght beſt here after auoyd that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible cryme of fylthy whordome and adultery.</p>
               <p>Then his diſcrete goſtlye father wolde exhorte hym, in any wyſe with all his due diligence dayly and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually to practiſe theſe wholſome pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeruatiues and moſte preſente reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies agaynſt whordo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e. that is to ſay.<note place="margin">Preſeruati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues from whordom.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Fyrſt, to exchue ydelneſſe and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> to be occupied in ſome honeſte laboure and buſyneſſe.</p>
               <p>Than, to auayde all occaſions of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> euel, al ſuſpecte houſes and wanton company.</p>
               <p>Agayne, to beware of fylthy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municacion, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> wanton ſonges and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of bawdrie, and nother ſpeake nor heare ſuche fylthynes.</p>
               <p>Further, to vſe ſobrietie and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraunce in the vſe of meate, drynke, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> ſlepe and apparel.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, to be dayly conuerſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> with ſuch perſones, as ar both chaſt, honeſt, vertuouſe and godly.</p>
               <p>Beſyde that, to remember daylye <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> what paynful paſſion &amp; death Chriſte ſuffred for our ſynnes and fylthy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feccions.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:21056:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>To conſyder alſo the certaintie &amp; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> ſuddenneſſe of death, &amp; what a ſtrayte accompte &amp; rekenyng muſt be gyuen of euery voyde worde muche more of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> fylthye actes and vnclennes. But ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially to vſe dayly, faythful &amp; feruent ſute, prayer and ſupplicacion vnto God for the gracious gyft of chaſtitie and clenneſſe of herte. And fynally, yf theſe be practiſed and wyll not ſerue nor ſuffice for the auoydyng of whor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in any wiſe to take a wyfe, for wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al other remedies fayle, that, wyth the practiſynge of the other wil ſerue. For that is the moſte preſent medicine and naturall remedie that God hath properly ordeyned to cure the diſeaſe of fylthye concupiſcence, whordome and adultery, after the do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctrine of S. Paule, whych ſayeth: To auoyde whordome let euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take hys owne wyfe,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.</note> and euery woman her owne huſbande.</p>
               <p>Thyrdlye, thys priuate confeſſion is chefly nedeful to them that are tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences,<note place="margin">For com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte.</note> &amp; are not fully purſuaded that their ſynnes are forgeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, by reaſon wherof they are halfe in deſperacion. Theſe I ſay haue muche nede of a diſcrete ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:21056:58" rendition="simple:additions"/> phiſicion to comforte them. For vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſſe their weake fayth be ſtayed and lyfted vp by ſome comfortable reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiues of the ſwete promiſes of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and mercy in Chriſte Ieſu, it is to be feared, that theyr goſtly enemy Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>than wyll ſhortly brynge them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperacion, and finally to euerlaſtyng damnacion. Therfore here the diſcret ſoule phiſicion wyl labour with tothe &amp; nayle to beate into thys ſpiritual pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tientes mynde and remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the moſte ſwete, playne and euident pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſes of Goddes ayde and aſſiſtence to be alwaye ready to them that aſke it in faythful prayer. Wherfore it is very nedeful to ſuche weaklynges in the fayth, that are ſo ſore broſed in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to make al the haſte that they can poſſible to the heardman of their ſoules, and playnly to open and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowlege their grefe vnto hym, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyrynge to heare of hys mouthe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable promiſes of grace in Chriſt Ieſu, to ſtaye and lyft vp their weake &amp; feble co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences. S. Iames ſayeth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iames</hi> 5.</note> Praye one for an other, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye maye be healed. For (ſayeth he) the ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er of a righteous ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auayleth much. Yf the prayer of one godlye perſone
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:21056:59" rendition="simple:additions"/> be of muche value, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prayers of two good chriſtianes agreyng toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prayer for any godly purpoſe, of more value.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 18</note> For Chriſt ſayeth: Yf two of you ſhall agre vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth (for what thynge ſo euer it be that they wolde deſyre) they ſhall haue it of my father which is in heauen. For where two or thre are gathered together in my name, there am I in the myddeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge them. Marke that Chriſte ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth: Yf two of you ſhal agre vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth &amp;c. And where two or thre are gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together in my name, there am I preſent amonge them. And I praye you is not thys weake faythed perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne and hys curate conſultyng of theſe matters gathered together in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes name? Yf they be (as vndoutedly they are) then is Chriſte in companye wyth them, by thaſſiſtence of his gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce and preſence of hys godhed. Again yf they two thus aſſembled do agree to pray together to God, for thencrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce and eſtablyſhment of the fayth of thys ſpirituall paciente, than ſayeth Chriſt vnto them thus: Yf two of you ſhall agre vpon earth (for what thing ſo euer it be that they wolde deſyre) they ſhall haue it of my father whych
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:21056:59" rendition="simple:additions"/> is in heauen. Good Lorde what a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable place of ſcripture is this? For we maye learne by it, that yf ther be but two perſonnes gathered togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Chriſtes name for any good and godly purpoſe, then is Chriſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent wyth them. And yf they agree to aſke any godly requeſte of God, they ſhal haue it graunted, what thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge ſo euer it be (ſayth Chriſte) ſo it be a godly requeſte conteyned wythin the limittes of fayth and charitie, and agreynge vnto the wyl of God.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5.</note> For S. Iohn ſayth: Yf we ſhal aſke any thynge accordyng to hys wyl, he hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs.</p>
               <p>But here one wyl ſaye:<note place="margin" type="runSum">Obiection.</note> Syr me thinke ye take the ſcriptures to ſtrayt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, yf you wolde bynd vs to confeſſe our fautes only to a preſte, or only to our own curate. For albeit S. Iames ſayth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iames.</hi> 5.</note> Knowledge your fautes one vnto an other, yet he ſayth not one la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye man vnto a preſte, nor one pariſho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner vnto his one curate and to no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but he ſayth generally one vnto a nother. Therfore I thincke that I maye aſwell make my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſyon to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other man as vnto a preſte, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to myn one curate.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:21056:60"/>
               <p>Truth it is, that thou mayſt frelye choſe any diſcrete chriſten man that is wel learned in holy ſcripture,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſwere.</note> &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorte to hym for learnyng, cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel and comforte: but yet for all that, ther is none ſo mete for thy purpoſe in that behalfe as thyne owne curate (yf he be no papiſt, neyther of corrupt iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement in the ſcriptures, but be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſte, diſcrete &amp; well exerciſed in gods holy worde.) For he is appointed of God to be herdman of thy ſoule, at whoſe mouth thou maiſt lawfully re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quire learnyng, cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, yea he is called &amp; apointed of God to preache vnto the, &amp; to al other his pariſhoners both priuatly &amp; apertly, ſecretly &amp; ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly the goſpell of Chriſte to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte thy ſoule wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nede is. Which preachyng of goddes mercye frelye gyuen to the faithful for Chriſtes ſake,<note place="margin">what is the true ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolution.</note> what other thynge is it than the true abſolucion of their ſinnes? For what other thing is the priuat abſolucion of the preſte, but a priuate or ſecrete preachinge of Chriſtes goſpel? what can the preſt more promyſe the ſynner by his abſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ther by to declare vnto him, that yf he repent hym of hys ſynfull lyfe, &amp; vnfaynedly purpoſe to amend,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:21056:60"/> repoſyng hys hole fayth, truſt &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the promyſes of grace &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy in Chriſt Ieſu, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> goddes truthe ſhal ſaue him for Chriſtes ſake? Can he promyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynner any other thyng than to be ſaued, yf he from the herte do repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, beleue, &amp; purpoſe to walk i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a new lyf? I thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ck not. Reſort therfor to thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one curat (yf he be honeſt, diſcret and wel learned, as I ſaid before) and thynke hym to be that perſone that is appointed of God, to miniſter Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes Goſpel &amp; hys ſacramentes vnto the, at ſuche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient tymes, as ſhal be nedeful to the comforte of thy trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bled conſcience.</p>
               <p>Ther is alſo an other kynde of pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uate confeſſion,<note place="margin">Confeſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of recoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation.</note> whych may aptlye be called, the confeſſion of reconciliacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. As whan I haue offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded my chriſten brother, &amp; haue prouoked hym to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. It is my bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den dutie to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile my ſelfe vnto him, &amp; to knowlege my faute, and deſyre of hym forgeue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe therof. This co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion is no leſſe than comau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of Chriſt to be done, &amp; he eſtemeth it ſo neceſſarie to be do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ꝓferreth it, &amp; wil haue it done, before we do any outward ſeruice, ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice, honour or worſhip vnto hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:21056:61"/> For thus he ſayeth: If thou offereſt thy gyfte at the Altare,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 5. <hi>Iob.</hi> 42.</note> and there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breſt that thy brother hath oughte againſt thee leaue ther thyn offering before the altare, &amp; go thy waye fyrſt, and reconcile thy ſelfe to thy brother, and then come and offer thy gyfte.</p>
               <p>Loo, here maye we ſe that Chriſte ſo muche regardeth the attonement of them that are at variance, and the mutual redreſſe of charitie, vnitie, pea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, and concorde betwene them, that he wyl haue that done before we ſhall be allowed of hym to do any accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruice or outwarde worſhip vnto hym. And truly I am muche afrayed that the tranſgreſſynge of this com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement of Chriſte, wyl condem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pne all moſte all the hole worlde, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caufe ther is ſo muche breache of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and ſo lytle regarde of mutuall reconciliacion and attonement. Howe be it they that are of God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated by hys holy ſpirite, wyl be very circumſpect and take good hede that they gyue no iuſte occaſion of an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gre vnto their neyghbour. But yf they chaunſe at any tyme (as al men are frayle) by theyr occaſion to offend and greue theyr euen chriſtian, yet
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:21056:61"/> they wyl ſeke al meanes to theyr poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible power, and wyth al the ſpede that they can, to be reconcyled againe vnto them. For who knowynge that he can by no meanes obtayne goddes fauour, onleſſe he be at one wyth his neyghboure, wyl not in thys poynte laye al worldly ſhame apart, and (ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mittynge hys obedience vnto the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemente of Chriſte) go to hys neyghbour, knowlege hys faute vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hym, and humbly deſyre the forge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueneſſe of his treſpace? Truly he that vnfaynedly feareth God, and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth earneſtly to auoyde hys diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, wyl not ſtycke to do thys godlye worke, but wyll be glad to do it and muche more.</p>
               <p>Beſyde al theſe former ſortes of confeſſion, ther was alſo vſed in the primatiue churche an open con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,<note place="margin">An open confeſſyon.</note> whych they that had bene ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated for great and haynouſe ſynnes, made before the hole congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion at ſuche tyme as they were re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtored agayne to the ſame. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this is nowe out of vſe (it is the more to be lamented) I wyl here ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke nomore of it.</p>
               <p>Thus haue I declared vnto you
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:21056:62"/> after my ſclender gyfte of knowlege what I haue redde &amp; marked in holy ſcripture touchynge the confeſſion of ſynnes. But wher as in the latter end of your letters you i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly deſyred me to wryte vnto you, what I thynke of the eare co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion that is now ſtraitly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded wyth you in Englande. Truly to vtter my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience playnly vnto you in fewe wordes, I thynke it bryngeth many a ſimple ſoule to the haſarde of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nacion.<note place="margin">Abuſes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>are confeſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyon.</note> For doutles ther are many ſhameful abuſes ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in, of whyche I wyll (by the grace of God) reherſe two or thre whiche are intollerable.</p>
               <p>Fyrſt, it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Through which abhominable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the ſimple co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people (for lacke of good inſtruccion) thinke, (for ſo are they diſceaued by falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> without eare co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion they can not be ſaued. So this opinion of neceſſitie of the one partie, &amp; the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſarie lawes made of ſtinckynge papiſtes for the maintenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me on the other partie, (I know this certeinly) bryngeth very many to per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plexed &amp; doutful ſtraites of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience. Whych (yf they be not in tyme remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:21056:62"/> by the ſwet promyſes of grace in Chriſte) wyl doutleſſe dryue them to deſperacion.</p>
               <p>Secondarely, It is no ſmale bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> of chriſten mens conſciences to compel them to nombre all their ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes particularly, wyth all due circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of tyme, perſone &amp; place, and howe many tymes euery ſynne was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted. Whych opinion perſuaded to the vnlerned people, is not vnlyke to bring many of their ſoules into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuels dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger. For chey thinke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (for ſo are they corruptly taught) to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe euery ſyn ꝑticularly by it ſelfe, &amp; to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; declare to their goſtly father euery circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the ſame. And yet ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>etime for fear, &amp; ſomtyme for ſhame they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe not al, but cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celeth &amp; hydeth ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e offence. Which not confeſſed, oppreſſeth their weake &amp; feble co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyme .iii. or .iiii. yeares or mo, &amp; ſo al that ſpace they thinke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues becauſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cealme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be in the ſtate of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nacion and quyte out of gods fauour. And many times (yf the thynge were tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly knowen) it is ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſo weygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty a matter as the eatyng of an egge vppon a frydaye, ſo depelye are the Popyſhe tradicions prynted in their
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:21056:63"/> in their tender conſciences, eſtemyng the breach of them to be a greater of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, then Idolatrie, blaſphemy, per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iurie, theft, ſlaunder or any tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of Goddes holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Whych thynge ought to make al the Babilonicall byſhoppes aſhamed (but that they are paſt al ſhame alrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy) becauſe they ſuffer Goddes people to be ſo drowned in ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not diſcerne the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dementes of God, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dirtie dregges of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtical tradicions. And albeit the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcripture alloweth theſe ſortes of confeſſion that I haue ſpoken of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this Epiſtle, yet for al that the proudeſt papiſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al can not finde in holy ſcripture theſe wordes or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences: To hys owne curate what ſo euer he is: Al ſynnes particularly: all circumſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces: and ſuche lyke traſh. For al theſe are nothyng els, but ped<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>larie patches of Papiſtrie. Whych I praye God maye be purged agayne &amp; bannyſhed out of Englande, and that ſhortlye.</p>
               <p>Finally, beſyde the forſayd abuſes of eare confeſſion the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſorte of people are therwyth two maner of wayes diſceyued. Fyrſt, becauſe they
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:21056:63"/> thynke, that their confeſſion is the cauſe of forgyueneſſe of their ſynnes, by reaſon wherof they blotte out the bleſſed benefite of the paſſion &amp; death of Chriſte, whyche is the onely obtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of grace and mercy for the ſinnes of all mankynde. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>darely, becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe they are fully perſwaded, that the penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faſtyng, prayer or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes enioyned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their gooſtly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the due ſatiſfaccion and ful re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>compenſacion to God, equiualent for their ſynnes paſt, whych they haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſed to the preſt: And ſo for lacke of knowlege &amp; inſtruccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vtterly diſceiued. For ſure it is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to god no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is able to ſatiſfye for ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne: for that ſatiſfaccion hath onely our ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt wrought in hys painful paſſion and death. I coulde here ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of many mo abuſes of eare confeſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion, but I wyll at thys tyme paſſe them ouer wyth ſylence.</p>
               <p>Thus muche haue I wrytten vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you of confeſſion of ſynnes, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare vnto you my conſcience and ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple iudgement therin, accordynge to youre requeſte in youre laſte letters wrytten to me by Nicolas Nerin fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rone in Fraunte the .8, daye of Ianu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>arie
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21056:64"/> in the yeare of our Lorde. 1555. And yf you accept this my rude wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting &amp; colleccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this matter. I ſhal by the grace of God do myne ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure lykewyſe in other matters of holy ſcripture to ſhewe you hereafter my ſmal and ſclender knowlege and iudgement. Thus the lyuynge God increaſe in you daylye more and mor fayth, charitie, mekeneſſe, godlyneſſe and pacience. &amp;c.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>From Copyn hauen in Denmark <date>the .3. of Februarye.</date>
                  </dateline>

                  <signed>By the rudehande of Your poore louyng frende Thomas Cotteſforde.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>If you wryte agayn to me wryte to Geneua for thetherwardes by Goddes grace I intende to go ſo ſhortly as I can.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:21056:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An Epiſtle vvrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>to a good Lady / for the comfort</hi>
               </hi> of a frende of hers, wherin the Noua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions erroure now reuiued by the Anabaptiſtes is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed, and the ſynne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte the holy Goſte playnly declared.</head>
            <p>MAdame, wher as it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed your good Ladyſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe to require me to write vnto you my mynd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernynge the true ſence and meanynge of thys place of S. Paule in hys Epiſtle to the Hebre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>It can not be that they whych were once lyghtned and haue taſted of the heauenly gyfte, and were become partetakers of the holy Gooſte, and ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue taſted of the good word of God, and of the power of the worlde to comme yf they fall awaye (and as concernynge them ſelues, crucifie the ſonne of God a freſſhe, and make a mocke of hym) that they ſhuld be renued agayn by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:21056:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Madame, Many in tyme paſt, and at thys preſent daye myſtakyng thys tex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te &amp; not truly vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dynge it,<note place="margin">The er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the Nouatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; now of the Ana<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>baptiſtes.</note> both haue bene and are encombred with the Nouacyons erroure, whyche is. That after man by baptyme and the holy Gooſt is regenerated, and hath taſted of the grace of God, and hath enbraced Chriſt and hys holy worde, yf he fall to ſynne agayn, he is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out remedye of ſaluacyon.</p>
            <p>Vndowtedly thys is a veray dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable errour, enoughe to brynge all them that are infected therwith to deſperacion. But albeit they grounde thys theyr erroure vpon thys a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alledged texte of S. Paule, &amp; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne other textes: yet they myſſe the cuſſion, becauſe they take thys ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to ſtraytly, not referryng it to many other places of ſcripture, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che playnly ſhewe: That when ſoeuer and howe often ſo euer a ſynner repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth hym truly of hys ſynnes, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth hymſelfe wyth a ſure faythe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mercy of God thorow Chriſt, God receyueth hym agayne to grace and ſaluacion.</p>
            <p>Doutleſſe no prophecie in the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture hath any priuate interpretacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Petri.</hi> 1.</note>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:21056:65" rendition="simple:additions"/> but muſte nedes be expounded accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to the generall articles of the Chriſten fayth and agreable to other textes of holy ſcripture, and ſo muſt thys texte be alſo.</p>
            <p>Nowe truth it is: that ther is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte innumerable textes in holy ſcripture, that moſt playnly do decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re: that whan ſo ouer a true repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner by vnfayned fayth returneth vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to god, &amp; aſketh mercy for chriſtes ſake, he ſhall vndoutly haue it. And albeit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcripture is ful of ſuch places, yet here by Goddes grace, I wyl ſhewe and reherſe to you ſome of them, to ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue you occaſion to marke them and ſuche lyke places as you ſhal fynd al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte in euery leaffe of the Byble.</p>
            <p>A iuſt man falleth ſeuen tymes, and ryſeth vp agayn.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 24.</note> Marke the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture ſayth: he ryſeth vp agayn.</p>
            <p>The wyckedneſſe of the wicked ſhal not hurte hym,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 33.</note> whan ſo euer he conuerteth. Note that it ſayth: whan ſo euer he conuerteth.</p>
            <p>Let the vngodly man forſake hys own waye,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 55.</note> and the vnrighteouſe hys own imaginacions and turne agayn vnto the Lorde, ſo ſhal he be mercyful vnto hym.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:21056:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Thou diſobedience Iſrael tourne a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gayn (ſayth the Lorde) and I wyl not let my wrath fal vpon you.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 3</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 8</note>Thus ſayth the Lorde: do men fal ſo, that they ryſe not vp agayn? Or yf Iſrael do repente, wyl not God turne agayn to them?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zacha.</hi> 1.</note>Turne you vnto me (ſayth the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de God of hooſtes) and I wyl turne me vnto you.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.</note>Remembre from whence thou art fallen, and do the fyrſte workes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 15.</note>Marke in the goſpel of Luke the ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ample of the vnthriftie ſonne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 22.</note>Alſo Chriſte ſayd vnto Peter: Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I haue prayed for the, that thy fayth fayle not, and whan thou art conuerted, ſtrength thy brethern. Marke, he ſayth: whan thou art con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted. Loo, yf you weye theſe places of ſcripture afore alledged, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt innumerable mo of the ſame ſorte, you ſhal perceaue euidentlye, that though a chriſtian haue ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer ſo oft (as who doth not dayly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend God) yet whan ſo euer he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth vnto God by true repentaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce (whych conſiſteth of inward contri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon and a ſure fayth in Chriſte Ieſu) he is aſſured by the worde of God to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:21056:66" rendition="simple:additions"/> recouer and receaue agayn the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, fauour and mercy of God, whych thorow his diſobedience he had wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely loſte, and immediatly to enioye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful, abſolute and perfecte remiſſyon and forgiuenes of al his ſynnes tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe Ieſus Chriſte, in whom he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth al hys fayth, truſte and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of ſaluacion.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.</note> The goſpel aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth hym no leſſe ſayinge: So God lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued the worlde, that he gaue hys only begotten ſonne, that who ſo euer bele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth in hym ſhuld not peryſh, but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue euerlaſtyng lyfe.</p>
            <p>More ouer, yf you marke wel the examples of godly men, whych are re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſtred in holy ſcripture, you ſhall playnly perceaue, that albeit they we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re hyghly in Goddes fauoure, yet for al that, many of them had greate fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and committed very heynouſe offences, but they dyd ryſe vp agayn returninge to Goddes mercy by true repentaunce and fayth, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered agayne their former grace, whych they thorowe theyr owne foly had loſt.</p>
            <p>Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was ſo much fauored of god, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by Goddes calli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g he was made the hygh byſhop &amp; curate ouer his people.<note place="margin">Aaron.</note>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:21056:67"/> And yet at the lyght requeſt of the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raelites, he let them make and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the golden Calfe contrarie to his conſcience, by reaſon wherof both he and they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted that moſte deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſynne of Idolatrie, and yet he by true repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taunce and fayth returning to grace was ſaued.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Dauid..</note>Dauid Goddes deare dearlyng, after that he had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowlege of God, and had muche taſted of hys grace, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynge indued abundantly wyth the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly gooſt and gracious gyftes from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, fel both into the ſynne of adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery and murther. And yet by true &amp; vnfayned repentaunce, returnyng to Goddes mercy was accepted and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued agayne into Goddes fauour.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Manaſſes.</note>Manaſſes alſo contrary vnto hys conſcience fel wyllyngly to Idolatrie but yet he roſe agayne by true repen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taunce and fayth, &amp; recouered again the grace of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian. <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note>So lykewyſe that wycked ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the cytie of Corinthus who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> S. Pau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le ſtraytly charged the Corinthians to exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate and exclude out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy congregacion of Chriſten men, and that they ſhulde neither eate nor drynke wyth hym, becauſe of his ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:21056:67"/> and abhominable cryme of inceſte &amp; outragiouſe whordome: and yet wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he declared hymſelfe to be truely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunt for hys great &amp; infamouſe ſynne. S. Paule admoniſhed them wyth al gentleneſſe and chriſten cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to receyue hym agayne into the congregacion as a chriſtian brother,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and ſo to eſteme hym and take hym.</p>
            <p>What ſhal I ſay of Peter Chriſtes Apoſtle?<note place="margin">Peter.</note> had not he a ſure knowlege of Chriſt, confeſſyng hym openly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the Apoſtles to be very Chriſt the ſonne of the lyuynge God? was not he euen than indued wyth the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gooſt and grace from aboue, vnto whome Ieſus Chriſt ſaid:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.</note> Bleſſed art thou Symon the ſonne of Ionas, for fleſhe &amp; bloude hath not opened that vnto thee, but my father whych is in heauen? And yet after al thys he had ſuche a fal, that contrary to his owne conſcience, willynglye wythout any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pulſion, threates, or impriſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, he dyd moſte cowardly and ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly forſake and deny Chriſt, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blaſphemye, ſweryng that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer knewe hym, curſyng and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng hym ſelfe to the deuel yf euer he had to do wyth hym.</p>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:21056:68"/>
            <p>What wold the Nouacian and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſte ſaye vnto thys? was it not a fal? could ther be any greater ſynne than thys? was it not done of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge? was it not done wyllyngly? was it not agaynſt hys owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? Yes doutleſſe, it was no leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe but agaynſt hys owne conſcience. But yet thanckes be vnto almyghtie God, it was not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynne of blaſphemy agaynſt the holy goſt, neyther the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne vnto death,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5.</note> the whych S Iohn ſpeaketh of, for he continued not ther in vnto hys ende, but immediatly he wente furthe of the byſhoppes houſe and wepte bytterly, very much lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting hys heynouſe offence, &amp; by fayth he returned agayne vnto Chriſt, kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng hys mercy to be infinite &amp; with out meaſure,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 26.</note> and ſo he was accepted vnto grace agayn, and Chriſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto hym (to his great comforte) after he aroſe agayn from deathe to lyfe, &amp; afterwardes ſendynge downe hys holy ſpirite, indued hym wyth wonderfull gyftes of grace from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue. And than Peter becamme a ſtronge champyon, ſettynge furth Chriſte to be the only ſauyoure of the whole worlde, preachynge and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:21056:68"/> confeſſing hym before al men, without any feare other of the ſcribes phariſeis or Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p>Now good Madame, laye thys ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ample of S. Peter to thys texte of S. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Paule to the Hebrues: It can not be that they whych were once lyghtned. &amp;c. Yf they fall awaye. &amp;c. that they ſhuld be renued agayn by repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</p>
            <p>If a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wolde applie the aforſayd example of S. Peter vnto thys texte of S. Paule, he wolde thinke that Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhulde vtterly haue ben caſt away from Goddes fauour mercy &amp; grace. For fyrſt it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be denied, but that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> he was once lyghtned, that is: indued wyth the true knowlege of Chriſte to be the only Meſſias and ſauioure of the worlde. Secondlye, he had <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> alſo taiſted of the heauenlye gyfte, whyche was a true faythe in Chriſte Ieſus, openlye confeſſynge the ſame before all the Apoſtles, beynge fullye perſuaded in hys owne conſcience what Chriſt was. Thyrdly, that Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> was beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me parttaker of the holy gooſt, &amp; had taſted of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good worde of God, it appereth euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly by Chriſtes ſentence, ſayeng: Bleſſed art y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:21056:69"/> for fleaſhe and bloude (that is man) ſhewed thee not that, but my father whych is in heauen. Whych was, by the inſpiracion of hys holy ſpirite. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Finally, Peter had a taſte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world to come. For he dyd ſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> montayne the tranſfiguracion of Chriſt, and ſo dyd Iames the more,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat,</hi> 17.</note> and Iohn the Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſt alſo. Wherin the preſence of them all Chriſt was tranſfygured and ſhewed hymſelf vnto them in the fourme of a glorifyed bodye, ſo that his face dyd ſhyne as the Sunne, and hys clothes appeared as whyt as the lyght. Ther appeared alſo among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Moſes and Elias. And euen there the cleare voyce of God the father of hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen was playnly herde amonge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the cloude, ſayeng vpon Chriſt. Thys is my dearly beloued ſonne, in whome I delyte. Heare hym.</p>
            <p>Loo, al thys and muche more Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter both herd &amp; ſawe, beyng almoſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinually in Chriſtes company, eating and drynkyng wyth hym, hearynge daylye hys heauenlye doctrine, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng and teachynge, ſeynge euerye where (as occaſion ſerued) hys great and wonderful myracles. And yet for al thys, what a great fall Peter had,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:21056:69"/> it appeareth playnlye by hys deniall of Chriſt hys louyng maiſter and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, and by the circumſtances ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, whych I touched before. But yet to make Peters fall more horrible, Chriſt ſayd vnto hym and vnto al the other hys Apoſtles, when he ſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forth to preache the Goſpel of ſaluaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: He that denyeth me before men,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.</note> I ſhall deny hym alſo before my father. Alaſſe good Peter, what caſe ſtandeſt thou in nowe? How doth thys ſayeng of Chriſt touche the? Remembringe thys ſayeng of Chriſt, art thou not vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly at thy wyttes ende? Is it not moſt certain &amp; true, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haſt to hor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ribly falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after that thou haddeſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of al theſe gracious gyftes before reherſed? Haſt thou not contrarye to thyne owne conſcience moſte ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully denyed thy maiſter and ſauiour Chriſt before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Ah good ſoule what ſhal beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of thee? howe wilt thou an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for thy ſelfe? For it ſemeth here playnly, that both S. Paule in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alleged place to the Hebr. &amp; alſo Chriſt himſelfe in the ſcripture afore reherſed haue gyuen ſentence of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the. Wherfore, bothe the Nouacion &amp; the Anabaptiſt grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:21056:70"/> them ſelues vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe two pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of holy ſcripture, wil plainly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the to be a reprobat, &amp; that thou art diſpatched &amp; vtterly caſt away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al hope of ſaluacion. But here let vs not to lyghtly paſſe ouer, but earneſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly waye &amp; depely conſyder, what may be ſayd in thys matter on Peters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe. And fyrſt it may be ryghtly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that that place of S. Paul vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the Hebrues,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.</note> maketh nothynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt S. Peter, neither yet agaynſt any chriſten man, howe greuouſly or howe often ſo euer he hath ſynned, ſo that he hath not vtterly forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt and fallen cleane awaye from hym. For S. Paule ſayeth: It can not be that they whych were once lyghtned. &amp;c. Yf they fal awaye. &amp;c. y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhulde be renued by repentaunce.</p>
            <p>Marke here diligentlye, that S. Paule ſayeth:<note place="margin">It is not al one thyng to fal, and to fal awa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ye. A pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe.</note> yf they fal awaye. He ſayeth not: Yf they fal. But: yf they fal awaye. For it is not al one thynge to fal, and: to fal awaye. For Peter dyd fal, but he dyd not fall awaye frome Chriſt, but returned vnto hym again An olde prouerbe it is: A man ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth very farre, that neuer returneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne. Al we chriſtianes do dayly fal,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:21056:70"/> for we dayly breake Goddes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementes, but yet we do not fal away from Chriſt, neither refuſe we hym to be our ſauiour, but acknowleging our manyfolde ſynnes and offences we dayly returne vnto hym agayne, by true repentaunce, faith and amen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement of lyfe, nothyng doutyng of hys great and vnmeaſurable mercye towardes vs.</p>
            <p>They fal awaye from Chriſt that vtterly forſake hym and refuſe hym to be their ſauioure,<note place="margin">who fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt</note> and neuer retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnto him agayne to obtaine his mercy, but are become playne apoſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taes, vtterly forſakynge the chriſten fayth, making but a mocke of Chriſt, perſeueryng in their obſtinate apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſye and vnbeleue euen tyll theyr lyues end:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Timo.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.</note> As dyd Iudas the traitour Iulianus apoſtata, Symon Magus, Porphirius, Hymeneus and Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Coperſmyth.</p>
            <p>Secondarely,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 10.</note> As touching that ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eng and threatnynge of Chriſt, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng: He that denyeth me before men,<note place="margin">A good &amp; general rule to be noted.</note> I ſhal deny him before my father. &amp;c. It is to be conſydered, that al the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible threatnynges that are in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:21056:71"/> ſcripture threatned agaynſte greate ſynners are threatned condicionally,<note place="margin">A good &amp; general ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> that is to ſaye: yf the ſynners do not truly repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te and returne vnto God by fayth and amendement of lyfe, thys plage and punyſhement or that, ſhall lyght vpon them. But yf they at the preachyng, readynge or hearynge of Goddes holy worde do repente and returne vnto God, by fayth &amp; godly lyfe, than that plage threatned ſhal not once touche them. Example by the Niniuites vpon whom Ionas Goddes miniſtre and preacher (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God by hym) pronounced thys terrible iudgement,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ione.</hi> 3.</note> ſayinge: ther are yet fortye dayes, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal Niniue be ouerthrowen. But ther as the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ſayth: the people of Niniue beleued God and earneſtly repented them of their greate ſynnes, and ſo was the ſentence of God retracted, and the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſaued and not ouerthrowne. So lykewyſe thys terrible ſentence of Chriſte: He that denyeth me before men, I ſhal denye hym before my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. muſt nedes haue thys condicyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ioyned with it:<note place="margin">A condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion.</note> If he doth not repent, neyther returne agayn: But Peter dyd both repence and returne agayn
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:21056:71"/> vnto Chriſte. For al be it hys fayth was weake and faynt (as was the fayth of al the Apoſtles) yet it was not vtterly extincte.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luce.</hi> 22.</note> For Chriſte had ſayd vnto hym befor: Symon. I haue pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed for the, that thy fayth fayle not. And in any wyſe take hede, and note thys wel: Chriſte ſayd not: He that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth me, I ſhal denye hym, though he repente and returne. But remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber well that Chriſte ſayd: I camme not to cal the righteouſe but ſynners vnto repentaunce.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.</note> Peter therfore re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pented, and returned vnto Chriſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayn, and ſo was receyued vnto gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and was ſaued.</p>
            <p>Wherfore good Madame, in thys harde texte of S. Paule vnto the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes, waye wel thys condicion: (Yf they fal awaye.) For they only fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye, whyche committe that moſte horryble cryme, which is called in the holy ſcripture, the ſynne vnto deathe, blaſphemye agaynſt the ſpirite, and the ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne agaynſt the holy goſt, which neuer ſhal be forgeuen, neyther in thys worlde neyther in the worlde to come.</p>
            <p>But here it myght be demaunded,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Queſtion.</note> what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynne agaynſt the holy gooſt
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:21056:72"/> is, and wherin it differeth from al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther greuouſe ſynnes. Wherunto I anſwere.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſwere.</note> That ther is difference in ſynnes, it maye clearly be gathered of Chriſtes wordes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 12.</note> ſayinge: I ſaye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you. Al ſynne and blaſphemie ſhal be forgyuen vnto men, but the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie againſt the ſpirite ſhal not be forgyuen vnto men.</p>
            <p>Loo, here is the matter playnly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened by our ſauiour Chriſte what kynd of ſynnes ſhal be forgeuen, and what neuer forgyuen. Blaſphemie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the ſpirite ſhal neuer be forgy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: al other ſynne and blaſphemie ſhall be forgyuen. And Chriſte in ſayinge: All ſynne ſhalbe forgyuen, compriſeth both original ſynne,<note place="margin">Thre ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Synne. Blaſphemy Blaſphemi againſt the ſpirite.</note> and alſo actuall ſynne. Moreouer Chriſte ſpeaketh here of thre ſortes of ſynnes. The firſte he calleth ſynne, the ſecond blaſphemie, &amp; the thyrd, blaſphemye agaynſt the ſpirite. Whych the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alſo calleth: the ſinne vnto death, and the ſynne agaynſt the holy goſt. Theſe thre kyndes of ſynnes, &amp; the dif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ference of euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I intende by goddes help ſeuerally to declare vnto you ſo ſhortly as I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſo for this ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitte you vnto god. And fyrſte
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:21056:72"/> conſyder wel what ſynne is.</p>
            <p>Synne is euery wylful diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, acte or dede,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Synne.</hi>
               </note> that is done contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vnto the lawe &amp; commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of God, without murmur, grudge or euel ſpeakyng other againſt the law, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes or God hym ſelfe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is the maker and giuer of the lawe. As is Idolatrie, ſuperſticion, periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſwerynge vnaduiſedly, breakyng of the holy daye, diſhonoryng father &amp; mother, murther, malice, hatred, en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uie, wrath, ſtrife, treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſedicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der, whordome, thefte and ſuch lyke.</p>
            <p>Al theſe and ſuch other are called, and are in dede ſynne, ſo longe as the doers of them do neyther murmur, repyne, grudge nor ſpeake euel agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte God or hys holy lawe, neyther a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe in their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience the thing and euel y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they do, but rather do vtterly diſalowe, accuſe &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne in thier owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce thoſe their owne da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble actes as euel and deteſtable. The ſeconde kynde of ſynne is Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemye, marke it wel, and conſider howe it differeth fyrſte from ſynne, &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſynne againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy gooſt</p>
            <p>Blaſphemie is more heinouſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſynne alone, for al blaſphemie is ſyn,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Blaſphem.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:21056:73"/> but all ſynne is not blaſphemie. For truth it is that blaſphemie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>priſeth in it ſelfe both ſynne, and alſo a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure, grudge, reuylynge, euel ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der &amp; reproche of god &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes, but it is alwaye coupled wyth ignoraunce and vnbelefe, and proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not of ſuche obſtinate malice as continueth to the ende of the lyfe, as doth the ſynne againſt the holy gooſt. In thys ſynne of blaſphemie S. Pau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le offended before hys conuerſion vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the fayth of Chriſt Ieſu.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1</note> For thus he ſpeaketh of hym ſelfe: Before, I was a blaſphemer, and a perſecutour and a tyraunt, but I obtayned mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, becauſe I dyd it ignorantly in vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beleue. Loo, here is it playne and eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that thys blaſphemie though it be a great offence, yet it is remiſſible and forgyueable, and is not excluded from grace and mercy, becauſe it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedeth of ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and not of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, nor of obſtinate malice that doth endure to the lyues ende. Neither is it the ſynne vnto death, and therfore we maye lawfully pray for ſuche blaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phemers.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5.</note> As S. Iohn ſayeth: Yf any man ſe his brother ſynne a ſynne not vnto death, let hym aſke, and he ſhall
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:21056:73"/> gyue hym lyfe.</p>
            <p>In thys ſymple blaſphemy (for ſo we may call it) many of the Iewes of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fended, takyng Chriſt to be nothynge leſſe, than the ſonne of Dauid, or Meſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſias, becauſe hys parentes were very poore, and himſelfe ſuppoſed to be but a poore carpenters ſonne, which bare but a ſymple porte in the worlde. Yea &amp; ſome of them that crucifyed Chriſte were ouerwhelmed in thys ſymple blaſphemie. And therfore Chriſt pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for them ſayinge:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 23.</note> Father forgeue them for they knowe not what they do. So Peter in hys ſermon excuſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crucifiers of Chriſte, ſayinge.<note place="margin">Act. 3.</note> Now deare brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I know that you haue done it thorowe ignoraunce. &amp;c. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pente you therfore and returne, that your ſynnes maye be done awaye. So dyd S. Steuen alſo praye for hys perſecutours,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 7.</note> whome before he called ſtyfnecked, aduerſaries of the holye gooſt, traitours and murtherers of Chriſt. Doutleſſe he wolde not haue prayed for them ſo earneſtly, vnleſſe theyr ſynnes had bene forgeueable. And therfore their ſynne and offence was no more but ſimple blaſphemie.</p>
            <p>¶The thyrde kynde of Synne, is
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:21056:74" rendition="simple:additions"/> blaſphemie agaynſt the ſpirite.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3</hi> Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the ſpirite.</note>They co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitte blaſphemie againſt the ſpirite, or ſynne agaynſt the holy gooſt, which willyngly, vpon know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, and aduiſedly, contrarie to their owne conſcience do deny, forſake, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne, ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, reuile, and perſecute the playne, open, manifeſt &amp; knowen truth, ſtyfly, maliciouſlye &amp; obduratly ꝑſeueri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g wythout vnfay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in that their wylfull blyndneſſe and obſtinate malyce ſo longe as they lyue in thys worlde. As dyd Pharao, Saul, Herode, Iudas the traytour, Iulianus apoſtata, Por<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phirius, Hymeneus and Alexander the Coperſmyth wyth other.</p>
            <p>But marke thys diligentlye: that we can not (as farre as I can percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue) certaynlye iudge of theſe blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers agaynſt the ſpirite, before the tyme of their departure out of thys preſent lyfe: becauſe we can not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynly knowe, whether at the ende of their lyfe they can repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; by fayth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne and take holde of the mercy of God,<note place="margin">Conictu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain. Luc. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> or not.</p>
            <p>We maye coniecture, but we can not (as I ſuppoſe) certaynly diffine of them. Let vs conſyder, that the theſe
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:21056:74"/> that hange on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryght ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of Chriſt, euen at the laſt houre repented, and wyth a ſtronge and faythfull prayer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted hym ſelfe wholly vnto the mercy of Chriſte, and was ſaued. In conſideracion wherof, let vs thinke it to be our bounden dutie (as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, Chriſt and hys Apoſtles dyd) to reuoke and cal backe agayne open ſynners and blaſphemers to earneſt repentaunce for theyr owne ſynful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to haue a ſure truſte in the mercye of God, and in the meryte of Chriſtes paſſion and death, thoughe they be euen at the departure out of thys preſent lyfe. For it is neuer to late ſo longe as lyfe laſteth. Let vs therfore wyth al feruentneſſe call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them &amp; exhorte them in any wyſe, with a good corage and a ſure and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doutful fayth aſke, call and crye for Goddes mercye, for hys ſwete ſonne our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, and vndoutedly they ſhal haue it. For ſyth the begynnyng of the worlde hyther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to was ther neuer one that in faythe aſked mercy hertely, but he had it, tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowe the graciouſe goodneſſe of oure aforeſayd moſte mercyfull Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte, vnto whome wyth the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:21056:75"/> Father and the holy Gooſt be all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure, laude and prayſe worlde with out ende. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours at co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement to al hys ſymple power Thomas Cotteſforde.</signed>
            </closer>
            <argument>
               <q>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.</note>Gyue all the honour laude and prayſe to God only.</q>
            </argument>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer_in_verse">
            <head>¶The prayer of Daniel turned into metre and applied vnto our tyme. Daniel. ix.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lorde thou hygh &amp; fearful God</l>
               <l>By who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e al thynges doth moue</l>
               <l>Thy mercyes great are ſure to ſuche</l>
               <l>As thy preceptes doth loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶We ſinful men haue ſore tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſt</l>
               <l>Agaynſt thy lawes diuine</l>
               <l>Full frowardly we haue fledde backe</l>
               <l>From theſe preceptes of thyne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶Thy prophetes dere to ſpeake were</l>
               <l>In ſettyng forth thy name.</l>
               <l>Both rych &amp; poore as bolde were bent preſt</l>
               <l>For to gaynſaye the ſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:21056:75"/>
               <l>¶To the therfore y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> Lorde of hooſtes</l>
               <l>All iuſtice doth belonge</l>
               <l>To poure on vs ſuche ſhame &amp; grefe</l>
               <l>In thys we haue no wronge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶Our ſhame is great &amp; due to al</l>
               <l>Our flyght is but in vayne.</l>
               <l>To tread ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge landes our ſyn hath ſought</l>
               <l>Our ſhame doth ſtyl remain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶But though ſuche ſhame a reward iuſt</l>
               <l>To al in common be</l>
               <l>Yet mercy Lorde and to forgyue</l>
               <l>Doth ſtyl belonge to thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶In dede (o Lorde) as for our ſelues</l>
               <l>No leſſe confeſſe we can.</l>
               <l>But that thy lawes we ſet at nought</l>
               <l>Muche leſſe haue kept them than</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶Thy prophetes ſpake we wold not heare</l>
               <l>Ne of thee ſtande in awe</l>
               <l>Strau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge plages fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyme to tyme we felt</l>
               <l>For breakynge of thy lawe,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶The ſorce wherof ſo fearſly bent</l>
               <l>Was ſuche as hath not ben.</l>
               <l>For all the plages in Moſes lawe</l>
               <l>Fell on thys realme for ſynne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:21056:76"/>
               <l>¶And yet to the who made his ſute</l>
               <l>Hys path waye ſo to gyde?</l>
               <l>That flyeng vice might learn thy law</l>
               <l>And therin to abyde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶Wherfore thou ſaweſt al wolde not help</l>
               <l>And couldſt not hold thyn hand</l>
               <l>But haſte thy curſe which now doeth fall.</l>
               <l>Vpon thys ſynful lande.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶For as thou arte a ryghteous God</l>
               <l>Thy workes do ſo appere</l>
               <l>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumyng ſuche as ſcorne doth take</l>
               <l>Thy louely voyce to heare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶But yet (o lorde) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> broughteſt forth</l>
               <l>Thy flocke from Egypt lande</l>
               <l>Wherby thy name was largely ſpreb</l>
               <l>So nowe ſtretch forth thyne hande</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶But we haue ſynned more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they</l>
               <l>Oh Lorde yet ſtaye thy rodd</l>
               <l>As for thys la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de was ſomtyme thyn</l>
               <l>And thou alſo our God.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶Our ſynnes &amp; eke our fathers faultes</l>
               <l>This daye to paſſe hath brought</l>
               <l>That al whych border vs about</l>
               <l>They ſet vs cleane at nought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:21056:76"/>
               <l>¶Now tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (o Lorde) hyd not thy face</l>
               <l>Oh heare thy ſeruauntes crye.</l>
               <l>Beholde thyne houſe ſomtyme ful ryche</l>
               <l>Howe waſt it doth nowe lye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy truth is fled, thy flocke faſt bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</l>
               <l>As ſhepe led to be ſlayne.</l>
               <l>Thy fooes preuayle &amp; proſper muche</l>
               <l>Though myſchefe they mayntayne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And wylt not thou thy fooes confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</l>
               <l>That thus thy workes reproue?</l>
               <l>At leaſt yet for thy names ſake</l>
               <l>Their vile intentes remoue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For why, as for our owne deſertes</l>
               <l>We can no ſuche thynge haue.</l>
               <l>It is for thy great mercies ſake</l>
               <l>That we ſuche thynges do craue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶Forgyue vs Lorde intreated be</l>
               <l>To heare vs make no ſtaye</l>
               <l>We beare thy name, it is thy cauſe</l>
               <l>Oh Lorde make no delaye.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
